<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Catholique iudge: or A moderator of the Catholique moderator Where in forme or manner of a plea or suite at law, the differences betweene those of the Reformed Church, and them of the Romish Church are decided; and without partialitie is shewed which is the true religion and catholique Church, for the instruction of either partie. Together with eight strong arguments or reasons, why the Popes cannot be competent iudges in these controversies. Written in the Dutch and French tongue, by Iohn of the Crosse, a Catholique gentleman. Translated out of French into English, by the right worshipfull and learned Knight Sir A.A.</title>
            <author>John of the Crosse, a Catholique gentleman.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04528</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14651</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107831</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843524</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843524</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8263</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04528)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8263)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 754:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Catholique iudge: or A moderator of the Catholique moderator Where in forme or manner of a plea or suite at law, the differences betweene those of the Reformed Church, and them of the Romish Church are decided; and without partialitie is shewed which is the true religion and catholique Church, for the instruction of either partie. Together with eight strong arguments or reasons, why the Popes cannot be competent iudges in these controversies. Written in the Dutch and French tongue, by Iohn of the Crosse, a Catholique gentleman. Translated out of French into English, by the right worshipfull and learned Knight Sir A.A.</title>
                  <author>John of the Crosse, a Catholique gentleman.</author>
                  <author>A. A., Sir.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 87, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I[ohn] D[awson] for Robert Mylbourne; and are to be sold at his shop, at the great south-doore of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dutch original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Variant: imprint has misprint "Mylborne".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8263:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8263:1"/>
            <p>THE CATHOLIQVE IVDGE: <hi>OR</hi> A MODERATOR OF THE Catholique Moderator.</p>
            <p>Where in forme or manner of a Plea or Suite at Law, the differences betweene thoſe <hi>of the Reformed Church, and them of the Romiſh</hi> Church are decided; and without partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie is ſhewed which is the true Religion <hi>and Catholique Church, for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of either partie.</hi> Together with eight ſtrong Arguments or Reaſons, why the Popes cannot be competent Iudges in theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies.</p>
            <p>Written in the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>French</hi> tongue, by <hi>Iohn of the Croſſe,</hi> a Catholique Gentleman. Tranſlated out of <hi>French</hi> into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> by the Right worſhipfull and learned Knight Sir <hi>A. A.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pro. 17.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Hee that iuſtifieth the wicked, and he that condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the iuſt, they both are an abhomination to the Lord.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>I. D.</hi> for <hi>Robert Mylbourne;</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop, at the great South-doore of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8263:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8263:2"/>
            <head>TO MONSIVER NICHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAS MALAYR, LORD OF <hi>TVT. &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir,<note place="margin">The Authors Epiſtle.</note> more then twenty yeeres are paſt ſince lighting on the ſubſtance or matter of this preſent booke, han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled in Latin, in forme of an Oration, by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement of certain good Perſonages, I was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to reduce it into the forme of an Action or Suite at Lawe, and to cauſe it to bee Printed in the <hi>Flemiſh</hi> tongue, with hope that this ſmall Treatiſe might conduce ſome-what towards the edifying of Chriſtians: And vnderſtanding that diverſe impresſions haue beene ſold in the <hi>Low-Countries:</hi> Hereupon I at the laſt reſolved to make it change language, for the vſe of our Churches, and eſpecially, of the Churches in the Kingdome of <hi>France,</hi> where
<pb facs="tcp:8263:3"/>
are to be found theſe two formall complaining parties, brought in as contending or pretending title in this cauſe of Religion: that is to ſay, they which make profesſion of the Romane Religion, as accuſers or Plaintiffes on the one part, and they which make profeſsion of the Reformed Religion as the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed or Defendants on the other part. I aſſure my ſelfe that both the one and the other will herein finde occaſion, more ſeriouſly to conſider of this ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant buſineſſe and debate; yea and whoſoever will not be wilfully blinde, may eaſily here diſcerne, how this ſuite or cauſe of Religion hath beene for many yeeres past wranglingly and cunningly pleaded, by them that ſeeke for nothing elſe but to charge and burden their adverſe partie with vniuſt and falſe accuſations, and reproches; and to hinder the comming at length to a finall deciſion or determination.</p>
            <p>God grant that even the moſt ſimple and ignorant may reade it heedfully, and without preiudice or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudging, to the end they may ſeriouſly reſolue to ioyne with the better party, for the advancement of Gods glory, &amp; of their ſaluation in our Sauior Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>For the reſt (Sir) I haue preſumed to dedicate vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you the <hi>French</hi> edition, of this religious ſuite or action concerning Religion: hoping you will accept, receiue, and take it in as good part, as I offer this my poore labour with a ſincere affection, eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I vnderſtand, that you are much addicted to the reading of bookes, which tend to the maintaining and defending of the doctrine of Ieſus Chriſt. Be pleaſed then (I beſeech you) that I may here make vnto you ſome ſmall publique acknowledgement and I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb facs="tcp:8263:3"/>
deſire our good God, to fit you with his eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all blesſings, moſt conducing and tending to his glory and your eternall ſalvation.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Harlem</hi> about the end of Ianuary, in the yeere of our Lord, <hi>1614.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your humble and moſt affectionate in ſervice and dutie.</hi> Iohn of the Croſſe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:8263:4"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Reader, whereas this little book containeth the principall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies of Religion, I thought good to adioyne hereto at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, a Catalogue of all the Authors, whoſe teſtimonies are cited in diuers places of this Treatiſe; to the end no man may thinke that the points or matter therein han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled is onely the opinion of ſome ſmall number of people, and of late ſprung vp, but of many perſons, and in ſundry times; to the end alſo, that every one dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently examining the ſayd authors, may ſatisfie and put himſelfe out of all doubt: So that neither the one nor the other party may haue iuſt reaſon to complaine of my partiality. Reade heedfully and iudge vprightly.</p>
            <div type="index">
               <head>A Regiſter of the Authors titled in this Treatiſe, for the better confirmation of the Truth.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>A</head>
                  <item>Auguſtinus.</item>
                  <item>Ambroſius.</item>
                  <item>Acatius.</item>
                  <item>Athanaſius.</item>
                  <item>Andradius.</item>
                  <item>Antonius Florent.</item>
                  <item>Aeneas Silvius.</item>
                  <item>Albertus Cratzius.</item>
                  <item>Abbas <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſpergenſis.</item>
                  <item>Auguſtinus Steuchius.</item>
                  <item>Arnobius.</item>
                  <item>Actius Zan.</item>
                  <item>Agrippa.</item>
                  <item>Apollo.</item>
                  <item>Arnulphus Aucet Epiſ.</item>
                  <item>Arias Montanus.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>B</head>
                  <item>Bernardus Abbas clu.</item>
                  <item>Baſilius.</item>
                  <item>Bonifacius.</item>
                  <item>Baldus.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8263:4"/>Benna Cardinalis.</item>
                  <item>Beda.</item>
                  <item>Baronius.</item>
                  <item>Bernardus Mendoza.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>C</head>
                  <item>Chryſoſtome.</item>
                  <item>Cyrillus.</item>
                  <item>Clemens Alexandrinus.</item>
                  <item>Cyprianus.</item>
                  <item>Calixtus.</item>
                  <item>Clementis Clementinus.</item>
                  <item>Coletus.</item>
                  <item>Conformiatum Liber.</item>
                  <item>Concilium Trident.</item>
                  <item>Coment. Magiſt. Pariſeen.</item>
                  <item>Cuſpimianus.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>D</head>
                  <item>Ducherius.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>E</head>
                  <item>Ecchius.</item>
                  <item>Evagrius.</item>
                  <item>Eutropius.</item>
                  <item>Extrauagants.</item>
                  <item>Euſebius.</item>
                  <item>Everard, Archi. Saliſ.</item>
                  <item>Epiphanius.</item>
                  <item>Eraſmus.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>F</head>
                  <item>Fellinus.</item>
                  <item>Francis Petrarch.</item>
                  <item>Flavius Blondus.</item>
                  <item>Fuccius.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>G</head>
                  <item>Gregorius Nazianzen.</item>
                  <item>Gelaſius.</item>
                  <item>Gulielmus Budaeus.</item>
                  <item>Gerſon.</item>
                  <item>Gregorius Magnus.</item>
                  <item>Gratianus.</item>
                  <item>Gabriel Biel.</item>
                  <item>Grebelius.</item>
                  <item>G. Lilius.</item>
                  <item>Gallen-Annal.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>H</head>
                  <item>Hironimus.</item>
                  <item>Hulderius Huttenus.</item>
                  <item>Heſius.</item>
                  <item>Hermoadus.</item>
                  <item>Hieron. Sauanarola.</item>
                  <item>Hiron. Marius.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>I</head>
                  <item>Ieremius.</item>
                  <item>Iuſtinian.</item>
                  <item>Iuſ. Canon.</item>
                  <item>Iaſon.</item>
                  <item>Ianus Pannon.</item>
                  <item>Iohannes Monlucius.</item>
                  <item>Iohan. de terra Cremata.</item>
                  <item>Iohan. Petrus Farra.</item>
                  <item>Iohan. Anarſimus.</item>
                  <item>Iohan. Iouianus Pontanus.</item>
                  <item>Iohan Functius.</item>
                  <item>Iohan Nouiamga.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>L</head>
                  <item>Lindanus.</item>
                  <item>Lombardus.</item>
                  <item>Laurentius Valla.</item>
                  <item>Luitperandus Ficinencis.</item>
                  <item>Legenda Sanctorum.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>M</head>
                  <item>Marcilius Ficinus.</item>
                  <item>Mantuan Baptiſta.</item>
                  <item>Mabeus.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8263:5"/>Marullus.</item>
                  <item>Matthaeus Pariſiens.</item>
                  <item>Michael Centonas.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>N</head>
                  <item>Nicholaus Cuſans.</item>
                  <item>Nauclerus.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>O</head>
                  <item>Oroſius.</item>
                  <item>Origenes.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>P</head>
                  <item>Paphnutius.</item>
                  <item>Panormitan.</item>
                  <item>Paulus Weigerius. Epiſcop.</item>
                  <item>Petruſius Soto.</item>
                  <item>Platina.</item>
                  <item>Petrus Premonſtra.</item>
                  <item>Pighius.</item>
                  <item>Philippus Orcius.</item>
                  <item>Pautalion.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>R</head>
                  <item>Raphael Volaterranus.</item>
                  <item>Ruardus Tap.</item>
                  <item>Ruffinus.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>S</head>
                  <item>Stella ventus.</item>
                  <item>Sabellicus.</item>
                  <item>Socrates.</item>
                  <item>Sigibertus.</item>
                  <item>Spiridion.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>T</head>
                  <item>Tertullianus.</item>
                  <item>Thomas Aquinus.</item>
                  <item>Theodoretus.</item>
                  <item>Trebellius.</item>
                  <item>Thomas Roden.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>V</head>
                  <item>Vincentius.</item>
                  <item>Valerius Anſelmus.</item>
                  <item>Vicaelius.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Z</head>
                  <item>Zezintus.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8263:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE CATHOLIKE IVDGE.</hi> All yee people and inhabitants of the world that loue the truth in ſinceritie of heart, be attentiue and giue eare, for behold a great and moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant cauſe is to be tried.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Soueraigne and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, who is a moſt gracious Father of all his elect, hath promiſed the Kingdome of Heauen to all true beleeuers, euen as to his deere Children, in his onely and well belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Sonne: And hath pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed and exhibited this his promiſe of the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inheritance, in the publike writings or records of the old and new Teſtament, and hauing alſo ſealed it with the Signet of the Sacraments, he hath ouer and aboue deliuered and committed it, into the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8263:6"/>
hands of the inheritors; Adioyning moreouer to the writings teſtimentarie, certaine fatherly conditions, which the heires of the ſame inheritance ſhould be tied to performe and obſerue. But the Children are fallen into debate, and they are deuided, and ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated one from the other, with great conteſtation. The one of the parties acknowledgeth the Pope of Rome to be their viſible head, yea verily and the Lieftenant of the heauenly Teſtatour. The other partie will not acknowledge the Pope of Rome to be ſuch: Euen thus they challendge and pretend right to the poſſeſſion of the heuenly inheritance, &amp; to the title of the true Church, the which each partie maintaineth, to appertaine vnto them: The Accuſer or Plaintife in this ſute is the Pope, together with all them that partake with him, or depend vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſea of Rome.</p>
            <p>The defendants or accuſed are all they that will not acknowledge nor admitt of the Pope, but make publike profeſſion of being of the reformed religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Both the one and the other parties, alledge their reaſons, their placards, and Charters, their letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, and writings ſealed, and produce alſo witneſſes depoſed: But both parties are much perplexed and troubled about chuſing of a Iudge: For each of them ſtriueth to propound ſuch a Iudge as thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueſt will be moſt fauourable and inclining to their ſide: The Church of Rome referres it ſelfe to the ſentence and iudgement of the Pope, of Traditions, of Councels, of auncient Fathers, and of miracles: affirming moreouer, that ſhee will not altogether exclude the word of God from this Iudgement or
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8263:6"/>
deciſion: Contrarie-wiſe they of the reformed religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on reiect and refuſe the Iudges aboue-named, ſaying that in this caſe or plea, the Pope of Rome cannot be at the ſame time both Iudge and partie, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring alſo that hee himſelfe is accuſed of diuers im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties. They reiect Traditions as ſuſpected Iudges and reproueable: Touching Councels the Fathers and miracles, they doe not acknowledge them for Iudges but rather for Antentike witneſſes, whoſe te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies they are ready to accept, ſo that they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the tenor or publike writings of the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Church of Rome accuſeth them of the reformed, to be reuolted or fallen away from the true Church, that they haue forged or deuiſed new deuine ſeruices. That they, haue not mooued this debate againſt them but within theſe few yeres: and therefore they affirme that the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and the title of the true Church belongeth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to all right and reaſon vnto them, and not in any ſort vnto the reformed.</p>
            <p>Theſe reply that they are not declined nor ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the true Church, but rather from the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue or Aſſembly, of the vngodly; that they haue not inuented a new doctrine, nor new Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but that they walke in the ſame way of Salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in which all the faithfull from the beginning of the world haue beene ſaued: That indeede in times paſt they haue beene oppreſſed by their tira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie; as <hi>Abell</hi> once was by his brother <hi>Caine, Iſacke</hi> by <hi>Iſmaell,</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi> by <hi>Eſau,</hi> ſo that they were forced to hide themſelues, but that now like the moone they haue againe recouered their light, attributing to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8263:7"/>
themſelues the names of firſt borne or Elderſhip. So that there is concourſe from all parts to theſe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and inheritours, which are at ſuch odds and debate, and great trouble and confuſion is rayſed. From words they paſſe to blowes, to murders, yea to ciuill warres, and ſhedding of bloud, to burning and hanging, and in breefe to all kinds of inhumane puniſhments and executions. Sometimes the one, another while the other partie ſeemes to haue the vpper hand: And the more they of the reformed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion are oppreſſed, perſecuted, burned, the more they boaſt of their aduancement, victorie &amp; triumph. In the meane time they proteſt, that men ſhould not in this caſe proceede by force and violence, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to right and reaſon. And herein they doe appeale to God himſelfe, not acknowledging any other head or Soueraigne Iudge, to the end that the Teſtatour himſelfe may determine this controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie by his laſt will which is contained in his holy word. And to the end that this may bee the more commodiouſly effected, they appeale alſo to an vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall Counſell, wherein it may, be freely permitted to reade and examine the codicells or ſcheduls, and the ſealed writings of the Teſtament, and by them to vnderſtand the laſt will of the heauenly Teſtatour. The Church of Rome on the contrarie part prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth that ſhee hath often cauſed generall Councels to bee aſſembled, in which the words of the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament haue beene ſufficiently examined, and that by them it is found and appeareth that the name and title of the Church appertaineth to none but to her onely. They of the reformed Church on the other
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8263:7"/>
ſide denie the ſayd Councels to haue beene vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall or free, for as much as the Popes haue not ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them there to render or make a free confeſſion of their faith, neither giuen them hearing of there defences, but contrarie to all right haue beene both accuſers and Iudges; hauing ſentenced and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the cauſe of there brethren without hauing heard there Allegations: Wherevpon they oft ſince proteſt, that they haue in noe ſort loſt their ſute and right; but that they will continue &amp; remaine, lawfull heires of the inheritance which was bequethed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them by their heauenly father, ſo long as they ſhal obſerue the conditions conteined in the Autentique writings of the Teſtament. In the meane while the reformed ſay, that they are prepared and determined to expect and tarrie for the iuſt &amp; Soueraigne Iudge Ieſus Chriſt, who will at length come to Iudge, both the quicke and the dead, and will make an end of theſe long controuerſies in religion, in ſuch ſort, as that he will grant and aſſigne to them that ſhall haue right, eternall life: but will caſt out them that are in the wronge to eternall condemnation. The two parties haue not proceeded any farther in this their action or demand. Now then the queſtion is to which of theſe two parties, the poſſeſſion of eternall life, and the title of the true Church ought to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged. True it is that this deciſion and iudgment appertaineth to Ieſus Chriſt aboue, the which alſo he will pronounce without farther appeale at the iudgement and Seſſion, which hee hath decreed, and notified to the whole world more then ſixteene hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeeres ſince, and without faile will come and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8263:8"/>
be within ſhort time. Be well adviſed and carefull in the meane time <hi>(O yee Kings and Princes, and all the Inhabitants of the earth)</hi> to ioyne your ſelues with the better party; leſt that now leaving this difference vndecided, Ieſus Chriſt, the ſoveraigne Iudge ſhould condemne you at his laſt comming in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And to the end you may pronounce iuſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in this controverſie in Religion, ſhew your ſelues vpright Iudges, and not partiall, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning either of the parties before you haue heard them. But if you haue hearkened with one eare as is meet, to the plea and doctrine of the Church of Rome; I deſire you to lend the other alſo to the plea and doctrine of the reformed Church: imitating herein <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, who was wont to heare the voyce of the accuſer with his right eare, in the meane while ſtopping his left one, which hee reſerved to hearken withall to him that was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed.</p>
            <p>I will propound then, and produce in the firſt place, the doctrine and opinion of both parties, and that out of the books and writings of each of them: <hi>bona fide</hi> I will neither adde nor diminiſh any thing at all, and I will here mention nothing that may not be found in their owne bookes litteral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in expreſſe tearmes. Afterwards, I will propound the arguments and reaſons, for which they of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed religion, refuſe to acknowledge and accept for their Iudges, the Popes, the Councels, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Traditions, Miracles, or other ſuch like wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes; but doe inſtantly require, that all ſuch diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of Religion, may be decided and determined
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8263:8"/>
by the written Word of God. And after you ſhall haue apprehended and conſidered all theſe things in the feare of God, and without any preiudicate conceit, or partiality: then I will willingly permit you to chuſe the better of thoſe two parties, preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding right, or contending one againſt the other.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The differences of the reformed Chriſtians, and the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Romanes touching the principall points of Religion.</head>
               <p>Concerning the firſt point, which wee haue at this preſent to entreate of: Behold, heare the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall and moſt important controverſies in the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of theſe two parties:</p>
               <p>Firſt, the reformed Church beleeveth,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture</hi> Io. 5. Io. 10. 1 Tim. 3.</note> that there is nothing neceſſary to ſalvation, which is not fully compriſed, or contained, in the holy Canonicall Scriptures, of the old and new Teſtament.</p>
               <p>But the Church of Rome ſaith,<note place="margin">Aug. <hi>49.</hi> cap. <hi>11.</hi> in Iohan. Petr. Sot. in Schol. de Scrip. Pig. de Ecleſ. hierar. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>14.</hi> Cenſ. col. pa. <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note> that the holy Scripture is vnperfect, and vncertaine or doubtfull; compareth the ſame holy Scripture to a noſe of wax, to a leaden rule; It affirmeth alſo, that without the authority of the Church, it is but as a fable of <hi>Eſops;</hi> that the Scriptures is the cauſe of al hereſies, that it is accommodated and applyed to the time, and that therefore the reading thereof muſt bee forbidden to Lay-people, that is to ſay, to the ſimple and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſort.</p>
               <p>The reformed Church beleeveth that credit muſt not be given neither to the Councels,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Of Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dions.</hi> Gal. 1. Eſay. 8.</note> nor to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, no nor to an Angell deſcending from heauen, if ſo be he ſhould teach contrary to the written word
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8263:9"/>
and doctrine of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. <hi>49.</hi> in Mat. Aug. lib. <hi>3.</hi> de Trin. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. Concil. Seſſ. <hi>4.</hi> Linden. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi> Hoſius de verbo in Sol. in Con. Late. enlo. pag. <hi>133. 3.</hi> Of the Law of God. <hi>Rom. 7. Mat. 5.1. Io. 1.</hi>
                  </note>The Church of Rome teacheth, that vnwritten traditions muſt bee held in as great eſtimation and reverence, as the holy Scripture, as being the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Faith, without which foundation the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and waight of the Scripture, vaniſheth away, or loſeth the reputation.</p>
               <p>The Reformed Church beleeveth, that the Law of God cannot perfectly bee fulfilled or performed by man: and that whatſoever is committed againſt the ſame Law, is ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. lib. <hi>2.</hi> con. Iuli. &amp; hom. <hi>48.</hi> in Ioan. Lindu. lib. <hi>3</hi> cap. <hi>19.</hi> Andrad lib. <hi>5.</hi> Ruord Tap.</note>The Church of Rome teacheth, that the Law of God may be ſo perfectly kept and performed, that one may doe workes of Supererrogation, or ſurpluſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage: alſo that all which is committed againſt the law of God is not ſinne; as amongſt other things concupiſcence.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>4.</hi> Of Sinne. <hi>1 Io. 3. Rom. 5</hi> Aug. lib. <hi>2.</hi> con. Iul. in hom. <hi>41.</hi> in Iron.</note>The Reformed Church beleeueth, that the want of originall iuſtice or originall corruption, concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, or coveting, and whatſoever is repugnant to Gods law, is ſinne, and maketh men culpable of the wrath of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Counl. Col pag. <hi>49.</hi> Ruor. Tap. de per. orig. Conc. Bes. Seſſ. <hi>36.</hi>
                  </note>The Church of Rome teacheth that concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence and originall ſinne, is not properly ſinne, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is ſubiect to the wrath of God, nor lyable to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">5. <hi>Of free-will.</hi> 1 Cor. 2. Rom. 7. Epheſ. 2. <hi>Aug. de Sp. &amp; lit. cap.</hi> 30.</note>The Reformed Church beleeveth, that ſince the fall, no free-will is left in man, touching things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to ſalvation, vnleſſe God change and moue the will of man by his holy Spirit.</p>
               <p>The Church of Rome teacheth that man can loue God <hi>Ex puris naturalibus;</hi> that is to ſay, only
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8263:9"/>
by his owne power and naturall facultie: Alſo that man euen being in mortall ſinne <hi>de congruo;</hi> that is to ſay according as is meete, proper or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable, may deſerue the ordinance or diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of grace.</p>
               <p>The reformed Church beleeueth that the elect of God are Iuſtified only by faith in Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>6</hi> Of Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. <hi>Rom. 3.4.5. Io. 3. Act 10.</hi> Aug. de Trin. Ser. <hi>114.</hi> Barn. ſup, cont. Ser. <hi>6.</hi> Con. Trid. Seſ. cap. <hi>11.</hi> Audred lib. <hi>6.</hi> pag. <hi>447.</hi> Sot. in Schol. de purga. Concil. Col. pag. <hi>156. 7</hi> Of the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Io. 3. 1 Tim 1. 1 Iohn 2. Math. 20. Eſa. 53.</hi> Aug. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>42</hi> in Iran. hom. <hi>85.</hi> Ambroſ. de Iſa.</note> without any good workes of the Law, in ſuch ſort notwithſtanding, as the ſaid faith, muſt not be vnfruitfull, or dead, but a true and liuely faith working by good deedes of Charity.</p>
               <p>The Romiſh Church teacheth, that men are not Iuſtified by grace and by the imputation of Chriſts Iuſtice, but by obedience of the law as our owne inherent righteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>The reformed Church beleeueth, that there is but one onely mediator betweene God and man; that is to ſay, Ieſus Chriſt very God and very man: who by his death and paſſion hath canceled and done away the ſinnes of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and by his reſurrection hath for them pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed and merited life eternall.</p>
               <p>The Church of Rome teacheth, that Chriſt died for originall ſinne onely. And that Ieſus Chriſt is not our only Mediatour, but together with him, all the he-Saints and ſhee-Saints of Paradice.</p>
               <p>The Reformed Church beleeueth,<note place="margin">8. <hi>Of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi> Heb. 10. 1 Ioh. 2. Heb. 9. &amp; 43. Eſa. 53. Act. 24.</note> that the faithfull are reconciled to God the father by the onely ſacrifice of Ieſus Chriſt, once offered and performed or finiſhed on the Croſſe.</p>
               <p>The Church of Rome teacheth, that the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8263:10"/>
death of Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Con Trid. Seſſ. <hi>6.</hi> con. <hi>2.</hi> Cat. Rom. pag. <hi>11.</hi> Gab. Bel. &amp; <hi>11.12.</hi> Linda. lib. <hi>4.</hi> pag. <hi>375.</hi>
                  </note> not the onely expiatorie and purging ſacrifice, but that the Maſſe is alſo ſuch an expiatorie or ſatisfying oblation, as abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſheth the ſinnes of the liuing, and of the dead; &amp; it is alſo availeable to obtaine all good things both ſpirituall and temporall.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">9 <hi>Of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi> Eph 4. Rom. 3. Io. 1. c. 19. Eſa. 19. c. 5.</note>The reformed Church beleeueth that ſuch a repentance is acceptable and pleaſing to God, wherein appeareth a true mortification of the old <hi>Adam,</hi> and a true viuification or quickning of the new man proceeding from a true faith</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lom. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Diſt.</hi> 16. <hi>Cat Rom. pag.</hi> 421. <hi>Com. Tho.</hi> 6 <hi>cap.</hi> 241. <hi>Con. Trid. Seſ.</hi> 4. <hi>And. lib.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 18. 10 <hi>Of the Church.</hi> Io. 10. Eph. 2. 1. Cor. 3. Math. 18.</note>The Church of Rome teacheth, that ſuch a repentance is requiſite in which there is a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect contrition of heart, confeſſion of mouth, and ſatisfaction of workes, by which onely ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation can be obtained.</p>
               <p>The Reformed Church beleeueth, that the true Church is, there where the word of God is ſincerely and purely preached, the Sacraments lawfully adminiſtred and diſtributed, and where the outward diſcipline of the Church is duly obeyed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Sot. def. lat: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'e pag. <hi>991.</hi> Iug. Con: Diſt. <hi>4</hi> Con Triden. Seſ. <hi>5.</hi> Con <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note>The Church of Rome teacheth, that the true notes of the Church are theſe: that is to ſay, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in publike doctrine with the Church of Rome: Secondly, the perſonall ſucceſſion of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; Thirdly, the acknowledgment of the Pope.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">11. <hi>Of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels.</hi> Mat. 18. Gal 5. Luk. 11. 1 Cor. 11. c. 119.12.62.</note>The Reformed Church beleeueth, that ſhee is not ſubiect nor tied to Councels, but onely to the written Word of God. Alſo that the Councells and auncient Fathers may erre, when
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8263:10"/>
they ſwerue, and turne aſide any whit from the word of God.</p>
               <p>The Church of Rome ſubiects and ties it ſelfe wholie to generall Councels as thoſe that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not erre.<note place="margin">Tap. Art <hi>1</hi> pag. <hi>5.</hi> Sot aſſen. lat de Concilijs.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Reformed Church beleeueth that there are but two Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts inſtituted by Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">12. <hi>Of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> Mat. 28. Mar. 16. 1 Cor. 11. <hi>Aug epiſt.</hi> 218. <hi>ad Ian. &amp; lib.</hi> 3 <hi>de doct. chriſt. cap</hi> 9. <hi>Con Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. Seſ.</hi> 7. <hi>can.</hi> 8. <hi>Linda. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 57. 13. <hi>Of Markes.</hi> Rom. 8. c. 3. 1 Timo. 2.</note> that is to ſay, Baptiſme and the Lords Supper.</p>
               <p>The Church of Rome teacheth, that there are ſeuen Sacraments which conferre ſaluation, <hi>Ex opere operato,</hi> that is to ſay, by the worke wrought yea euen without any good intention or affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe that vſe them.</p>
               <p>The Reformed Church beleeueth, that the afflictions and oppreſſions which the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full endure in this world are fatherly correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are ſent vnto them from God, for their amendment &amp; the chaſtiſment of certaine ſins, or elſe are trialls and proofes of their faith or teſtimonies of the true doctrine they ſuffer for.</p>
               <p>The Church of Rome teacheth,<note place="margin">Linda. lib. <hi>4</hi> cap. <hi>73.</hi> Con. Triden. Seſ. <hi>4.</hi> Can. <hi>9.</hi> Tho. Aquin. l <hi>4.</hi> Diſt. <hi>4.</hi> Art. <hi>9.</hi> Sot Aſſeu: de author.</note> that the Martirdom or ſuffering of the Saints is an expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie or purging oblation for ſinne; and that the paine or puniſhment which they endure, deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth a diminiſhing, and mitigation of eternall puniſhment, and moreouer life eternall.</p>
               <p>The Reformed Church beleeueth,<note place="margin">14. <hi>Of the Magiſtrate.</hi> Rom. 13.</note> that the Magiſtrate ought not only to take care of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining and defending the temporall goods of his ſubiects: but alſo of true religion, and of procuring their ſaluation.</p>
               <p>The Church of Rome teacheth,<note place="margin">Sot. in late. ſchol. Ibid. in aſſirt. Cap.</note> that the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8263:11"/>
muſt be debarred from entermedling with Eccleſiaſticall affayres, and with religion, and alſo that Eccleſiaſticall cauſes pertaine on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Pope and his Prelates.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">15 <hi>Of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</hi> Heb. 15. 1 Cor. 7. 1 Tim. 3.1. <hi>Chriſoſt hom. in Tit.</hi> 2. <hi>con. diſt.</hi> 28 <hi>Pigh. cat. Rom pag</hi> 552.</note>The Reformed Church teacheth that Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age is honorable among all: And that it is a Diueliſh doctrine to forbid it to any.</p>
               <p>The Church of Rome affirmeth, that ſuch as are married liue in the fleſh, and that marriage is forbidden to Prieſts, and to Eccleſiaſticall perſons: And that it were more tolerable, for an Eccleſiaſtical perſon to entertaine many Whores and Concubines, then to betake himſelfe, to lawful marriage.<note place="margin">16 <hi>Of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> Col. 2. Mat. 11. 2 Iohn 1. Eph. 2. Gal. 3. Mat. 15. <hi>Con. Triden. Seſ. can.</hi> 1. <hi>Cat. Rom. pag.</hi> 319 499. <hi>Can. Triden. Seſ.</hi> 4. <hi>can.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Grat. con. diſt.</hi> 5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Reformed Church beleeueth, that chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me or annointing with oyle, and other ſuch like obſeruations, and traditions of the Church of Rome, are directly repugnant and oppoſite to the word of God.</p>
               <p>The Church of Rome teacheth, that by the Sacrament which they call confirmation, the faithfull receiue more graces then by the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Baptiſme, And that extreame vncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on confirmeth ſpirituall grace.</p>
               <p>The Reformed Church beleeueth, that none can be Iuſtified before God by any other meanes then onely faith in Chriſt Ieſus.<note place="margin">17. <hi>Of Vowes.</hi> Io. 1. Heb. 10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Church of Rome maintaineth, that vowes of continency, pouertie, and obedience merrit eternall life.<note place="margin">Sot. aſſer. Can. And pag. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>The reformed Church beleeveth, that their ſins are aboliſhed and blotted out by the blood of the onely Mediator Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:8263:11"/>The Romane Church beleeue, that there is not onely a divine vertue in holy water, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo an efficacie to cure, and heale, and to driue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way diuels; and in ſumme, to defend and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue all things, againſt all inconveniences.</p>
               <p>The Reformed Church beleeue,<note place="margin">20. <hi>Of Invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi> Exod. 20. Mat. 4. Act. 4. Apoc. 12. 1 Ioh. 4. <hi>Ecch. in Lom. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>diſt.</hi> 48. <hi>Con. Trid. Seſſ.</hi> 6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. <hi>Lind. l.</hi> 3.23.</note> that we muſt call vpon God the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt, in ſpirit and in truth.</p>
               <p>The Church of Rome maintaineth, that we muſt call vpon Angels, and hee-Saints, and ſhee-Saints of Paradiſe; attributing to each Saint a particular office: as for example, that Saint <hi>Leonard</hi> delivereth priſoners, that Saint <hi>Valentine</hi> giveth bodily health, Saint <hi>Roch,</hi> or Saint <hi>Petronel,</hi> cureth the fever, Saint <hi>Clare</hi> the diſeaſes of the eyes, and Saint <hi>Anthony</hi> the tooth-ach.</p>
               <p>God commandeth that none but hee alone ſhould be honoured, worſhipped and adored.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>21.</hi> Of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques. <hi>Deut. 4.</hi> Con. Trid. Seſſ. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>The Pope commandeth to honour and adore the bones, reliques, and images of the Saints.</p>
               <p>The reformed Church beleeveth,<note place="margin">22. <hi>Of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting.</hi> 1 Tim 4. Col. 4. Rom. 14. Mat. 15. <hi>Soc. de iciun.</hi>
                  </note> that the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding of certaine meates, on certaine dayes, out of an opinion of merit, and holineſſe, is a doctrine of Divels.</p>
               <p>The Roman Church teacheth, that abſtaining from certain meats is a work by which one may ſatisfie for ſin, and by which a man may apply vnto himſelfe the merits of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The reformed Church beleeveth,<note place="margin">23. <hi>Of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences.</hi> 1 Ioh. 1.2.</note> that the blood of Ieſus Chriſt is the expiation or ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for our ſinnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:8263:12"/>
                  <note place="margin">Terrae Pro. <hi>11.46 62.</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trava li. Tit. <hi>9.</hi> Clem. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note>The Church of Rome teacheth, that the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons and Indulgences of Popes are able to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine not only abſolution of temporall and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall puniſhment: but moreouer, eternall ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>7.</hi> Of the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute power or rule of the Pope. <hi>Epheſ. 4. Col. 1.</hi> Cent fro. Ie. de Turr. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>64.</hi> Fol. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cent. Rom.</note>The Reformed Church beleeveth, that Ieſus Chriſt is the onely head, who was crucified for vs, and now raigneh with great Maieſtie at the right hand of his heavenly Father.</p>
               <p>The Church of Rome affirmeth, that Ieſus Chriſt is an inviſible head, and that the Pope of Rome is the viſible head of the Church, who ſurmounteth all Emperours, and Monarches, ſo much as the Sunne excelleth the Moone, or as gold exceedeth lead. Alſo that he is greater then <hi>Moſes,</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul;</hi> that hee is like to Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> yea verily that hee is God, and not man: that hee may alſo diſpoſe and diſpence contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the foure generall Councels, and againſt the words of the Goſpell.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">25. <hi>Of the certainty of faith.</hi> Mar. 9. Rom. 8. <hi>Aug. pag.</hi> 4. <hi>tit.</hi> 6. <hi>cap</hi> 2.7.</note>The Reformed Church beleeveth, that the faithfull ſhould not doubt at all of their ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>The Romane Church teacheth, that we muſt alwayes doubt thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">26. <hi>Of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt.</hi> 1 Ioh. 2. Mat. 24. Dan. 12. Apoc. 17. 1 Theſ 2.</note>The Reformed Church beleeveth, that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt is already come; and that hee is Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt that denyeth Chriſt Ieſus to bee come in the fleſh, that is to ſay, who maintaineth falſe doctrine, touching the nature and office of Ieſus Chriſt. The throne or ſeat of which Antichriſt is erected, in the Citie ſtanding vpon ſeaven hills.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:8263:12"/>The Church of Rome expects yet the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt from <hi>Babylon,</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Dan;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Comp. Theſ. l. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi> &amp; <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> who ſhall beare rule three yeeres, and at the laſt ſhall be ſlaine vpon the mount of Oliues.</p>
               <p>The Reformed Chriſtians beleeue,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>27.</hi> Of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory. <hi>Io. 5. Apoc. 19.</hi> Cat. Rom. pag. <hi>127.</hi> Com. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olo. l. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi> Inguſt. propo.</note> that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after the death of their bodies, their ſoules ſhall be carried vp to heaven, into life eternall.</p>
               <p>They of the Romane Church ſay, that there is a Purgatorie; yea, that there are fiue places for the ſoules of the deceaſed. 1. The hell of the damned. 2. The place of children, which haue not beene baptized. 3. Purgatory. 4. <hi>Limbus,</hi> or the ſuburbs of hell, where the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs are. 5. Heaven.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="reasons">
               <head>Eight reaſons why the Popes cannot be competent Iudges of Religion.</head>
               <p>BEhold in briefe the differing doctrine and controverſie betweene theſe two parties: The Church of Rome referreth it ſelfe to Popes, to Councels, to Fathers, to their Church, and to Traditions; affirming that they ought to bee Iudges, and pronounce ſentence and definitiue reſolution in all theſe controverſies.</p>
               <p>The Reformed refuſe all theſe Iudges, before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named, adding there-withall, their reaſons wherefore they reiect them. I earneſtly then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat thee (friendly Reader) as thou holdeſt deare and pretious thine owne ſalvation, yea ſo farre forth as in this debate and variance of theſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8263:13"/>
contending inheritors, thou deſireſt to ioyne with the better party, that thou wilt indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and patiently hearken to them both.</p>
               <p>Now then concerning the firſt Iudges pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by them of the Romane Church, that is to ſay, the Popes of Rome.</p>
               <p>The Reformed defendants or accuſed, ſay, that they cannot acknowledge, nor admit them for competent Iudges in this cauſe, for diuerſe very pregnant reaſons. For firſt, they ſhew, that the Popes of Rome long time ſince, haue not onely beene accuſed, but alſo convinced of eight horrible crimes and impieties, and that by the moſt part of Chiſtendome: that is to ſay, <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland, France, Hungarie,</hi> the greater part of <hi>Germany, Switzerland, Denmarke,</hi> and <hi>Sweden;</hi> yea likewiſe of the Churches and Nations, which haue made, or now make profeſſion of Chriſtian religion, in <hi>Africke,</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> in <hi>Syria,</hi> in <hi>Greece,</hi> and in other quarters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The crimes and impieties of the Popes are:</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Impiety or Atheiſme.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Tyranny.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Corruption of religion.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. <hi>Sacriledge.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. <hi>Treaſon.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>6. <hi>Perfidiouſneſſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>7. <hi>Antichriſtianiſme.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>8. <hi>Together with ten pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like diſgraces and infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The Reformed Chriſtians affirme, that they can proue and ſhew the prophane impiety of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8263:13"/>
Popes by theſe three arguments and reaſons.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="reason">
               <head>Irreligion the firſt cauſe of refuſall diuided into three reaſons.</head>
               <p>Firſt in that they attribute vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues a Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:<note place="margin">The Firſt reaſon. Diſt <hi>96.</hi> cap. Satis c. quoniam deminb. Diſt. <hi>39.</hi> diſt <hi>40</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi> papam: plu de conſell. <hi>37</hi> no <hi>3.</hi> vel. <hi>7.</hi> Iuſen. Conſe. <hi>145</hi> no <hi>2.</hi> vel. Bas l. vel. Son fol. cap. Egono de Iure.</note> For there owne ptinted bookes maintaine that they are Gods: that they are not ſubiect to any perſon in the world; that they are the ſpouſe of the Church: that they may tolerate, diſpoſe, and diſpence, directly againſt the Apoſtolicall Canons or rules; beyond and aboue al lawes and priuiledges. Briefly that they muſt not be queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by any perſon, whether they are this or that, although they ſhould dayly condemne an infinite number of ſoules into hell.</p>
               <p>Secondly the Reformed ſhew the impietie or prophanes of the Popes,<note place="margin">The ſecond, reaſon.</note> becauſe they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues haue often ſcoffed at their owne religion and deuine ſeruice: For <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſeuenth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced or drew on a certaine man ſo farre by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of a great ſomme of mony that hee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke to kill the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> the third with a beame which hee would cauſe to fall vpon his head,<note place="margin">Benon. Cardin.</note> when he ſhould be in the Church offering vp his praiers withall deuotion: but as the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer made haſt to execute his murder, the peece breaking which vpheld the ſayd beame, vpon which hee did ſit, the murderous fellow and the beame fell downe from on hie both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
               <p>The ſame Pope <hi>Hildebrand</hi> conſulting with
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8263:14"/>
diuels againſt the Emperour,<note place="margin">Stella Venitus lib. ad cardin. <hi>5.</hi> maro. Raphael voluter.</note> made no difficultie to caſt the body of the Sacrament of Chriſt into the fire, euen againſt the will, and liking of the Cardinalles: which act the Biſhop of <hi>Parma</hi> hath diuulged and diſcouered. <hi>Silueſter</hi> the ſecond, obtained that authoritie papall by diueliſh practiſes vpon condition that after his death, he ſhould be abandoned and left to the Diuels.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth cauſed <hi>Bandin Iulian</hi> to bee murdered in the Church by certaine Ruffins hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for that purpoſe; to whom he gaue the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſigne and token by the hoſt of the Maſſe: For that the Popes eſteeme not verie much their Euchariſt or Hoſt, it appeareth euidently, as the reformed ſay, becauſe that ordinarily, they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt or commit it to an horſe-keeper which carries the ſame before on horſe-backe, among the Scullions of the kitchin; as being the Auaunt and courier of the Popes comming.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The third reaſon.</note>Thirdly the Reformed maintaine that they can alſo prooue the prophaneſſe or impietie of the Popes, becauſe they haue inſtituted more then ſixtie fiue Eccleſiaſticall orders; euerie of thoſe orders hauing a diuers faſhion, of attiring and of ornaments, and, veſment according to the diuers and ſundrie cuſtomes or faſhions, rules &amp; orders of their Couent. And among all theſe orders the number of the Cordeliers or Friers minors,<note place="margin">Sabellicij. Enuead. <hi>29.</hi> l. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> of ſome is eſtimated in Europe only at more then fiue hundered thouſand; which may eaſily be gathered by that, which the generall of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8263:14"/>
the order of Saint <hi>Francis</hi> hath often promiſed and offered to the Pope; that is to deliuer vnto him about the number of thirtie thouſand Monkes, which without any hinderance of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſeruice might all be imployed in the warrs. So it is that amongſt all other orders the Corde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers and Iacobines are held much to excell all the reſt. And the Cordeliers (beſides all other fables which one may reade in the booke of the Conformities of Saint <hi>Frances</hi>) are not aſhamed to call vpon their patron in theſe latine verſes.
<q>
                     <l>Franciſſe, Ieſu tipice dux norma<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Minorum.<note place="margin">See. lib. con. Fo. <hi>228.</hi> Col. <hi>4.231.</hi> Col. <hi>1.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Sedes nobis perpetuò da regni caelorum.</l>
                  </q>
that is to ſay;
<q>
                     <l>Good Saint Francis head of Friers minors,</l>
                     <l>which of Ieſus Chriſt art the true figure:</l>
                     <l>Cauſe vs to haue part of heauenly honours;</l>
                     <l>and life to obtaine that ever doth endure.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And the <hi>Iacobins</hi> are ſo bold as not onely to compare there Saint <hi>Dominicke</hi> with our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">See epiſt. Flor. Aut. intust. part. <hi>3.</hi> art. <hi>23.</hi> &amp; <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note> but which is more in many thinges they placed him afore Ieſus Chriſt. The golden legends of the he-Saints and ſhee-Saints are all at this day printed, which ſufficiently ſet forth the fained miracles of one <hi>Staniſlaus Adulbertus</hi> and of ſuch other Saints. And for ſo much as the Popes approue and allow ſuch bookes, yea and propound them to Chriſtians to be held in equall honour and reuerence with the written word of God:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aut.</hi> 23.27. <hi>fo.</hi> 137.</note> From thence alſo the Reformed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:8263:15"/>
Chriſtians conclude, that the Popes are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="reason">
               <head>Tyranny the ſecond cauſe of refuſall.</head>
               <p>The ſecond reaſon for which the Reformed will not accept the Popes for their Iudges,<note place="margin">The ſecond reaſon.</note> is, that they haue vſurped dominion and ſoveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ouer the Church. For firſt of all the Pope cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth himſelfe to be ſtiled the Head, the Spouſe, and Soveraigne Biſhop of the Church: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, that title cannot properly appertaine to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſon, but Chriſt Ieſus alone. In the ſecond place, becauſe that the Pope will beare rule and haue ſoueraignty over all the earth, and all the Potentates of the earth.<note place="margin">Of the donati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine.</hi>
                  </note> For touching the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, by which they ſtriue to confirme their dominion and rule, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that it hath beene heretofore ſharpely que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned, by <hi>Nicolaus Cuſan, Laurentius Valla, Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laterranus, Aeneas Silvius,</hi> and diverſe other very learned Authours, the which notwithſtanding haue not ceaſed to bee patrons and defenders of the Romane Sea. The Reformed Chriſtians maintaine, that they can convince the ſayd do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of falſhood and vntruth, by theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons following.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Ten reaſons by which it is proved, that the donation of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, is falſe and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit.</head>
                  <p>Firſt, becauſe none of the beſt and moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooved
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8263:15"/>
Authors, either affirme, or ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of this donation of <hi>Conſtantine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Becauſe that <hi>Euſebius</hi> and other ancient Hiſtorians, teſtifie, that the Emperor <hi>Conſtantine</hi> divided the three parts of the world to his three ſonnes.<note place="margin">Socr. Theolo. Evagr. Ruffin. Okeb. Beda. Sozom. hiſt. pan. <hi>2</hi> Vol. lib. grn <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Becauſe the Inſtruments and Decrees which touching the ſame were imprinted, are very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, and their ſtile no whit agreeing.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That it is an abſurd thing, and likewiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible, that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould haue appeared to <hi>Conſtantine</hi> in his ſleepe, and that hee ſhould haue adored them as gods.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. That hee was never infected with the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. That he was not baptized by <hi>Sylveſter</hi> at Rome, but by <hi>Euſebius in</hi> Nicomedia.<note place="margin">Alb. Krant. in Sax lib. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>1.</hi> Manſil. indefenſ. part. cap. <hi>11.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. That it is a prophane kinde of ſpeech, to ſay that the hand of God was ſeene by <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8. That he could not giue to the Pope a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter right, then he had himſelfe.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. That hee could not conferre or beſtow vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Pope power or authority over the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> the ſayd title at that time being not built nor finiſhed.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. And laſtly,<note place="margin">Euſeb. de vita Conſtan. Ruff. l. <hi>1</hi> c. <hi>39.</hi> Viues l. <hi>24.</hi> hiſt. Beul. de Con. Nue, l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> becauſe ſuch donations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the priviledges and grants made to the Popes, which they haue received from the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> are the certaine markes of Antichriſt.</p>
                  <p>Surely by all theſe reaſons aforeſayd, it mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8263:16"/>
appeareth ſay the Reformed) that ſuch do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation was never made to the popes by <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> but that it hath beene forged and counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited by the Popes themſelues. And concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the wordes of our Saviour Chriſt, pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> and to all other Preachers &amp; Teachers of the word of God,<note place="margin">Aug in Io. tract. <hi>10</hi> &amp; <hi>12.</hi> &amp; de ver. dom. Ser. <hi>20.</hi> Cyril. in Dial. de Trin. lib <hi>4.</hi> Ambr. Epiſt. ad Epheſ. cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> ſaying; <hi>Feed my ſheepe:</hi> this ſentence and ſpeech doth not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port or ſignifie a politique and outward domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion or authority, but onely the miniſtery of the Goſpell. For in another place our Lord Ieſus Chriſt taxeth the ambition of the Apoſtles, for that ſome would beare rule and haue dominion over other ſome, and for that vpon this occaſion they entred into conſultation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Chryſ. hom. <hi>55.</hi> in Math. Ber. Epiſt. <hi>230.</hi> Mat. <hi>20.25.</hi> Diſt. <hi>4.</hi> ca. multi quicun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> cap. <hi>1.</hi> Sedis diſt. <hi>99.</hi> ſi quis. <hi>7.</hi> Der. de por.</note>The Kings of the Nations (ſaith Ieſus Chriſt) beare rule over them, but it ſhould not bee ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you: yea and the very Canons haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly forbidden that the Biſhop of Rome ſhould be called Soveraigne Biſhop, or vniverſall head of the Church (wherefore ſay the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) the Popes beat themſelues with their owne rodde, ſeeing they cannot rightfully attribute or appropriate to themſelues ſuch authority and domination, and that for diverſe cauſes and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="reason">
               <head>Corruption of Religion the third cauſe of refuſall.</head>
               <p>The 3. reaſon which the Reformed Chriſtians produce, for which they will not ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8263:16"/>
to the iudgement of the Popes, is this; that they haue not only intricated and confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded religion and divine ſervice with many vaine ceremonies,<note place="margin">Can. <hi>9.</hi> diſt. <hi>34.</hi> Can <hi>4.</hi> in diſt. <hi>82.</hi> Can praeb. lib. decretal. Greg. tit. <hi>7.</hi> can. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> but haue alſo groſſely erred in doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine. For ſome decrees affirme of the Popes, that they are not men but gods; that they cannot bee iudged by any perſon in the world; that they may diſpoſe and diſpenſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Apoſtles; that they can change the properties of things; that they can make ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of nothing; that they haue power to make iuſtice of iniuſtice.<note place="margin">Io. 1.4. 2 Tim. 3. Mat. 15. Gal. 1. Ier. 7. <hi>Iren. Epiſt.</hi> 4. <hi>Con. Trad.</hi> 4. <hi>con. li. cer. per. ſur.</hi> 7.</note> Now how exceeding falſe all this is (ſay the Reformed) it appeareth by that which almighty God teſtifieth himſelfe, that there can be but one forme of religion, that is to ſay, that which is contained in the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Prophets and of the Apoſtles: yea verily, that an Angell from heauen hath no power to adde thereunto, nor from it to dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh. Whereas the Pope for all that, will haue religion to conſiſt in humane traditions ſuch as are the <hi>Agnus Dei</hi> which they call,<note place="margin">2. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milian.</hi>
                  </note> the baptiſme of Bels, the invocations of Saints, the ſingle life of Prieſts, the withdrawing or depriving of the Cup in the Lords Supper,<note place="margin">De coen. dom. lib. <hi>3.</hi> decret. Greg. tit. <hi>41.</hi> Cal. cum. diſt. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> the vſing of a ſtrange language, and not vnderſtood in the outward ſervice of the Maſſe, Buls, and Indulgences, and other like traditions, all which as they ſay, came to them from the Apoſtles. Although it is moſt cleere and evident by ancient Hiſtories, that they haue for moſt part been inſtituted long after by the Popes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues: For Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:8263:17"/>
the giving of the Cup in the Lords Supper to Lay-people,<note place="margin">When and by what Popes the traditions of the Church of Rome haue been inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> following the decree of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terane Councell. Alſo hee ordained that the conſecrated bread ſhould be received only vpon Eaſter-day, which bread is more properly called the Euchariſt, or bread of thankeſgiuing. <hi>Euge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> the fourth, Decreed the contrary, in the Councell of <hi>Baſill. Innocent</hi> and <hi>Honorius</hi> inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted that the conſecrated bread ſhould be reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and kept for diverſe and ſundry purpoſes, in Churches, with great veneration and reverence. Contrariwiſe Pope <hi>Clement</hi> would not ſuffer the ſayd bread to be kept and reſerved till the next day. <hi>Vitilian</hi> the ſecond, and <hi>Agatho</hi> or <hi>Agathus</hi> the firſt, did decree that the Maſſe ſhould be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred in Latine: And <hi>Nicholas</hi> the firſt, on the other ſide gaue leaue to the <hi>Sclavonians</hi> and <hi>Polonians,</hi> to adminiſter and ſing the Maſſe in their owne language. <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſecond, commanded not to heare the Maſſe, which was ſung by a Prieſt that had a Concubine: on the contrary ſide, <hi>Lucius</hi> the third, permitted it. <hi>Siricius Pelagius</hi> the ſecond, &amp; ſome other Popes haue condemned the mariage of Prieſts. And oppoſite to that, <hi>Pius</hi> the ſecond, hath left in writing this ſentence: That marriage was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred vnto Prieſts, for a pregnant and weighty cauſe. But that it muſt be allowed vnto them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine for a reaſon more vrgent and peremptory. <hi>Leo</hi> the firſt, <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſecond, and third, and diverſe other Popes, haue approoued of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of Images. Contrariwiſe, <hi>Iohn</hi> the 23.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8263:17"/>
greatly deteſted Images in the Church. <hi>Boniface</hi> the fourth gaue power and authoritie to Cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers to preach, to Baptize, and to giue abſolution. Contrarie wherevnto, <hi>Gregorie,</hi> depriued them of that power, <hi>Iohn</hi> the 24.<note place="margin">Con. <hi>16.</hi> qua. <hi>8.</hi> adijcing.</note> held for a ſound article of faith, that the Apoſtlos neuer made vowe of pouertie, and of continencie. <hi>Pius</hi> the ſecond ſaid, that begging Monkes were the ſlaues of the Diuells adding theſe verſes:
<q>
                     <l>Non audet ſtigius daemon tentare, quod audet,</l>
                     <l>Effraevis Monachus, plena<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> fraudi anus:</l>
                  </q>
that is to ſay.
<q>
                     <l>The verie Diuell Dares not vndergoe,</l>
                     <l>What lawleſſe Monke, and craftie hugge wil doe.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pelagius</hi> the firſt, ordained that Clerkes ſhould daily read houres which they cal of ſeuen houres long <hi>Gregorie</hi> the firſt, commanded them to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme their ſeruice not by ſinging, but by tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and preaching publickely. <hi>Calixtus</hi> ſaith, that it is not lawfull to beleeue otherwiſe then the Church of Rome doth, Pope <hi>Iulian</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Boniface</hi> commanded to celebrate the Iubilie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie hundereth yeere; whereas <hi>Clement</hi> the ſixt hath reduced &amp; ſhortened it to the fifti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h yeere; <hi>Boniface</hi> the ninth to the three and thirtieth. And <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourh to the 25. and <hi>Hadrian</hi> and <hi>Leo</hi> the third gaue authoritie to the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> to choſe the Popes. But <hi>Stephen</hi> the fourth and <hi>Hadrian</hi> the fourth, and <hi>Sergius</hi> the ſecond,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8263:18"/>
haue aſcribed the ſayd authoritie to the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall perſons, to the Magiſtrate and to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Rome; And <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſecond did on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly permit it to the Cardinalls: Finally the Whore <hi>Matilda</hi> choſe to bee Popes, <hi>Victor</hi> the third, and <hi>Vrbane</hi> the ſecond. As alſo the Harlet <hi>Theodora</hi> elected <hi>Iohn</hi> the eleuenth;<note place="margin">Ficinenſis lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi> Popes lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ignorant or vnlearned.</note> the Strumpet <hi>Marozia, Sergius</hi> the third; <hi>Antheras</hi> ordained that none ſhould be choſen Pope who had not firſt beene Biſhop. Contrariwiſe to which decree <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the ſecond, and <hi>Benedict</hi> the eight, were Lay perſons, <hi>Benedict</hi> the ninth, and <hi>Iohn</hi> the ſecond, were altogether ignorant and vnlearned.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Can. omnibus vtriuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>.</note>
                  <hi>Gregorie</hi> the firſt, did forbid to eate fleſh, milke, Cheeſe, Butter, Egges, on faſting dayes; <hi>Eleutheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> ordained contrarily that no meate ſhould ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitiouſly bee refuſed. <hi>Innocent</hi> the third brought in Auricular confeſſion. <hi>Nectarius</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch of Conſtantinople on the other-ſide did abrogate it, becauſe that vnder coulour of confeſſion an Adulterie was committed. <hi>Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> the third inſtituted the eliuation,<note place="margin">De conſe. diſt. <hi>1.</hi> can. vata diſt. <hi>96.</hi> can. vbi. nom.</note> lifting vp of the bread in the Maſſe. <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ninth that a little bell ſhould be rung at the ſame In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. And <hi>Innocent</hi> the fourth, that at the very inſtant men ſhould fall on their knees. <hi>Zephirin</hi> brought in Challices of glaſſe inſtead of wodden ones: And <hi>Vrban</hi> Chalices or Cuppes of gold in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtead of glaſſe. <hi>Nicholas</hi> the firſt, excluded from the Counſell, Emp. as being lay perſons. One the other-ſide <hi>Marcellus, Damaſus,</hi> and <hi>Iulius</hi> permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8263:18"/>
them to aſſiſt and be preſent at Councels.<note place="margin">Plat devitis. Pontifi.</note> 
                  <hi>Stephen</hi> aboliſhed openly the decrees of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> the ſecond <hi>Stephen</hi> the ſixt likewiſe reiected the decrees of <hi>Formoſus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Romanus</hi> the firſt diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulled the decrees of <hi>Stephen</hi> the ſixt: and <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus</hi> thoſe of <hi>Romanus:</hi> and <hi>Damaſus</hi> thoſe of <hi>Liberius,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> the ſecond, thoſe of <hi>Pius</hi> the ſecond.</p>
               <p>Behold (ſay the Reformed) the Traditions,<note place="margin">Alphon. con. haereſ. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi> Here. Marcel. Eckine. Iohan Gerſon.</note> decrees, and Canons, which the Papiſts would attribute to the Apoſtles, Behold the Chriſtian Religion which the Popes of Rome boaſt to haue preſerued and continued ſo ſincere and pure: without ſaying any thing of the moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt hereſies of the Popes: that is to ſay that Pope <hi>Honorius</hi> was a Monothelite, that <hi>Liberius</hi> was an Arrian, that <hi>Marcellinus</hi> ſacrificed to the Idols of the Pagans, that <hi>Anaſtatius</hi> was a Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinian, and <hi>Iohn</hi> the 22. held opinion that ſoules periſhed and died before the day of Iudgement.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="reason">
               <head>Sacriledge the fourth cauſe of refuſall.</head>
               <p>The fourth cauſe and reaſon why the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Chriſtians will not conſent to receiue the Popes for their Iudges, is their Simonie.<note place="margin">The fourth reaſon.</note> For it is verie cleare and manifeſt, that the Popes ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther together more gold and ſiluer by Annates, firſt fruites, or vacanties, by preſentations, reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations in fauour, recommendations, diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, for age and regularity of bodily infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties by graces or fauours expectatiue, reuoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8263:19"/>
benefices, vacant, exemptions of viſitations, creations of notar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s and protonotaries Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, for non obſtantes, for Indulgences, to ſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler Prieſts for reuocations, for tolleration and ſuffering of Concubines, and for diuers ſuch like chaffers; then all the Romane Monarches e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer could collect or rayſe from all the quarters of the world, during the time that the Romane Monarchie was in moſt flouriſhing eſtate. There is extant at this day a complaint in writing of the Kingdome of France,<note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of the Kingdome of France touching the Popes Simonie</note> that the Popes had wont yeerely to draw out of the Realme only about eight and twentie tunnes of gold. Diuers other ſuch like complaints of kings may be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily found out, yea of Clerkes themſelues and of other great Eccleſiaſticall perſons; all which accuſe verie greatly the Simonie of Popes. And how true all it afore-ſaid is; it manifeſtly appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by the onely example of <hi>Iohn</hi> the 22.<note place="margin">The exceſſiue treaſure of <hi>Iohn</hi> the 22.</note> who left after his death, in his owne treaſurie about the ſumme of two hundereth and fifteth tunnes of gold: As <hi>Francis Petrarch</hi> an author worthie of credit doth plainly teſtifie. <hi>Boniface</hi> the ſeuenth ſeeing he could ſtay no longer at Rome in ſafetie; by ſtealth conueyed away out of the Cheſt or Shrine of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> the moſt preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Iewels kept therein &amp; fled to Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. <hi>Clement</hi> the eight, and diuers other Popes, haue beene often conuinced by their owne fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes of ſuch like ſacriledges. <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ninth ſold to the Emperour his abſolution for an hundered thouſand ounces of gold. <hi>Benedict</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:8263:19"/>
the twelfth, being poſſeſſed with feare, ſold to <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſixt the Popedome, for fiue and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hundred pounds of ſilver. The ſimonie of <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt, is alſo ſufficiently knowne by his Epitaph, which is yet freſh in memory:
<q>
                     <l>Vendit Alexander, Coelos, Altaria, Chriſtum:</l>
                     <l>Emerat ille prius, vendere iure poteſt.</l>
                  </q>
That is to ſay;
<q>
                     <l>Heaven, Altars, Chriſt, did Alexander ſell:</l>
                     <l>He bought them firſt, ſell them he might as well.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Furthermore, how <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth, cauſed to be ſold by <hi>Tetzalias,</hi> and diverſe other Popes by their Emiſſaries or Legats, their Indulgences, Buls, &amp; pardons, is better knowne throughout all Chriſtendom, then is wel-pleaſing to the Popes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="reason">
               <head>Treaſon the fift cauſe of refuſall.</head>
               <p>The fift cauſe wherefore the Popes cannot be good Iudges in the differences (ſay the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) is the crime of high treaſon or conſpiracy;<note place="margin">The fift rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> for they proue by true Hiſtories, that in all times they held the Emperours, Kings,<note place="margin">Extrava. de maior. &amp; obed. Can. <hi>1.</hi> extra. Mat. conſ. Extra de ma. &amp; obed.</note> and Princes of all Europe, not onely for their vaſſals, and liege-men, or homagers, but alſo for their vile ſlaues, and baſe ſervants. Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> alighting from his horſe, as the Emperour <hi>Fredericke Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baroſſa,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Emperor horſe-keeper to the Pope.</note> with great reverence approached to the right ſide of his horſe to hold his ſtirrop, the Pope was offended at the fault committed by
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:8263:20"/>
the Emperour,<note place="margin">Hol. chron. <hi>5.</hi> Cal. cap. <hi>8.</hi> Nau. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Gen. <hi>79.</hi> Ram. in vit. Pontif.</note> reproving him ſomewhat ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whereupon the Emperour ſtill full of devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion anſwered in excuſe, that it ſo fell out with him, becauſe hee was not accuſtomed to hold ſtirrops, and that it was the firſt time he ever ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed ſuch an office. And the Popes choller being the more ſtirred by ſuch an excuſe; the Emperour ſaid vnto him, I would faine know whether this my ſervice proceed from good-will or from dutie: If it come from good will, who will taxe for any negligence him that is officious and ready to do ſervice? And if it proceede not of dutie, it imports not much on which ſide he holds the ſtirrop, who came but to ſhow and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme courteſie and ſeruice? The next day the Emperour met the Pope, and being become more circumſpect by the foreſaid reprehenſion held the left ſtirrop, ſo conducting and guiding the Pope towards his armie: Behold ſurely an exceeding contempt and diſgrace of ſuperiour authority.<note place="margin">Nau Ga. <hi>39.</hi> Bern. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pen. Funct. in cron.</note> And yet the Reformed affirme that they can produce a greater deſpitefulnes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignitie, that is to ſay, of <hi>Alexander,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Pope after <hi>Adrian</hi> aforeſaid: For hee ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving excommunicated the ſaid Emperour <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dericke Barbaroſſa,</hi> when he requeſted to bee ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved of his excommunication, the Pope aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him a certaine day, vpon which hee ſhould appeare in the great Church of <hi>Venice:</hi> whither being come into the preſence of this Pope, and of many Cardinalls and Biſhops; hee would not giue him his abſolution, vnleſſe firſt he proſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:8263:20"/>
and caſt himſelfe downe at his feete, entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting pardon of him: The which the Emperour doing, the Pope lifted vp his foot, and put it on his neck, cauſing at the inſtant his Prelats to ſing that verſe of the 91. Pſalme,<note place="margin">Platin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt walke vpon the Lion and Aſpe, the young Lion and the Dragon ſhalt thou tread vnder thy feete:</hi> Wherewith the Emperour being much diſpleaſed, anſwered hereunto: Not vnto thee, but to Saint <hi>Peter:</hi> but the Pope treading the ſecond time on the Emperours necke, replyed both to mee and to Saint <hi>Peter.</hi> And the Hiſtory of <hi>Philip</hi> the faire, King of France, agreeth very well with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: For whereas the ſayd King was by <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight baniſhed, or accurſed as an Heretique and Enthuſiaſt. The King notwithſtanding, ſurceaſed not to proceed in his reſolution: And after hee had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced the ſaid Pope by evident teſtimonies, of diverſe grievous faults and offences, hee cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to be impriſoned in Rome. And as this Pope entred like a Fox, and raigned as a Lion, in the end hee died like a dogge. In the yeere 1300. a great number of people of all Nations being aſſembled in Rome to celebrate the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilie, the ſame <hi>Boniface</hi> ſhewed himſelfe to the people the firſt day, adorned with pontificall veſtments and attyre;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The Pope beares the two ſwords.</hi> Abbas Veſp. in P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a. Annal. Gal. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. in Euſeb. cap.</note> and the next day appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in Imperiall habite, cauſed a naked ſword to be carried before him, crying with a lowd voyce, I am Pope and Emperour; I haue Signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orie or Dominion earthly and celeſtiall. And a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:8263:21"/>
few dayes after, when <hi>Albert</hi> who was choſen Emperour by the Electors, requeſted to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the ſayd Pope; hee refuſed at the firſt entreaty, ſaying; that ſuch an Election as was made without his commandement &amp; authority, ought not to be eſteemed for good and lawfull; yet within a ſhort time after, he condeſcended to the deſire of the Emperour, but vnder this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that vpon the firſt occaſion offered, hee ſhould invade the kingdome of France. <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, did ſo hate the Emperour <hi>Philip,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee was choſen Emperour againſt his will, that he often-times ſayd: Let either the Pope take away the Imperiall Crowne, or let <hi>Philip</hi> take the Apoſtolicall Diademe from the Pope.<note place="margin">Ab Veſp. Ser. Plat. Marſ an. Gal. &amp; imper.</note> 
                  <hi>Clement</hi> the ſixt, ſayd to the Embaſſadors, that hee would never giue abſolution to their King <hi>Lodowicke,</hi> or <hi>Lewis,</hi> for his offence; vnleſſe free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly yeelding vp his kingdom, he committed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with his kingdome and all his goods into the Popes power, with promiſe not to accept nor receiue againe any of thoſe things, but from the meere favour and onely grace of the Pope.</p>
               <p>The Reformed adde moreouer to the former, that vpon the ſame foundation and ground, Pope <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the firſt, was the firſt that cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Emperour to kiſſe his feet: That <hi>Martin</hi> the fift, cauſed the Emperour <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> to doe the like; as alſo <hi>Iohn</hi> the 17. <hi>Creſcent</hi> Conſull of Rome;<note place="margin">Emperours ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated by Popes.</note> and <hi>Benedict</hi> the third, the Emperour. Moreover, ſay the Reformed, this ought not to be paſſed over in ſilence, that is to ſay, that Pope
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8263:21"/>
                  <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, excommunicated <hi>O tho</hi> the fourth, as alſo <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſeuenth excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, and <hi>Paſchall</hi> the ſecond,<note place="margin">Aug. ſtan. lib. <hi>2.</hi> de. Conſt. pag. <hi>138.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the fift, <hi>Adrian</hi> the fourth, and <hi>Alexander</hi> excommunicated <hi>Fredericke</hi> the firſt, <hi>Innocent</hi> the third <hi>Philip,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Fredericke. Gregorie</hi> the ninth, <hi>Fredericke</hi> the ſecond, and that three ſundrie times, to be briefe <hi>Innocent</hi> the fourth, <hi>Conradus</hi> the fourth: And all this was done for the moſt part becauſe they would not in all things performe the will of the Popes. And euen ſtill at this preſent the greateſt part of kings, and Realmes, Princes, and Potentates, of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome are in ſubiection to the Pope as his vaſſales and homagers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="reason">
               <head>Perfidiouſneſſe the ſixt reaſon of refuſall.</head>
               <p>In the ſixt place,<note place="margin">Perſidiouſnes the ſixt reaſon of refuſall.</note> the Reformed accuſe the Popes of perfidiouſneſſe or faithleſneſſe and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, ſhewing by auncient Hiſtories worthy of credit that the Popes haue euer tended to this end and purpoſe; &amp; ſo ſoone as they vnderſtand that any difference and diſſention was raiſed or ſet on foote betweene kings and great Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates, to entertaine and nouriſh the ſame debate and diſſention by their Emiſſaries and Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, but yet according or compounding with the one or the other partie, that if ſo be either of the two could vſurpe or obtaine that kingdome of his aduerſarie, that then he ſhould make ſome acknowledgment to the Romane ſee for ſo good and happie ſucceſſe. And ſo ſoone as the ſayd
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:8263:22"/>
accord and ſecret conſpiracie paſt, was conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto, the aduerſe partie was forth-with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated by the Popes as an heretike, &amp; his realme expoſed as a prey, to whomſoeuer would invade or conquer it firſt, by puting in for it. The which the reformed ſhew by expreſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples: for touching the firſt, although the king of France, <hi>Lewis</hi> the 12. deliuered to the Pope <hi>Iulius,</hi> two certaine Cities, ſo it is, that the Pope not therewith contented did caſt him out of his protection, and expoſed his realme to devaſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or ſpoile.<note place="margin">Arnobius Benn. Iuil Bul. maſſe lib. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> And whereas the ſame Pope <hi>Iulius</hi> for diuers wicked and ſcandalous facts (which are hereafter recited) was ſuſpended from his papall authoritie by the Counſel of <hi>Piſa,</hi> (albeit the ſayd Counſell was diſturbed by the ſayd Pope, and tranſported to <hi>Lions</hi>) he was enraged with ſuch choller, that he was reſolued to leauie an armie, and to enter into France, and when al things were in readineſſe, and himſelfe mounted on horſe-backe he cauſed the ſouldiers to paſſe through the Citie of Rome,<note place="margin">The Pope caſts S. <hi>Peters</hi> Keyes into Tiber, and drawes S. <hi>Pauls ſword.</hi>
                  </note> beyond the riuer Tiber, and pronounced alowde and plainely theſe wordes in preſence of many thouſands of people. Goe to, ſince the keyes of S. <hi>Peter</hi> are no more availeable, let vs vnſheath the ruſtie ſword of S. <hi>Paul:</hi> and therewithall caſting Saint <hi>Peters</hi> keies into Tiber, he drew his ſword threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with a grim and frowning countenance and gnaſhing his teeth, to ruinate and vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Frenchmen. The enſample of <hi>Philip Auguſtus</hi> is alſo like to the former, for the ſaid
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:8263:22"/>
king <hi>Philip</hi> hauing conquered from the Engliſh a great part of his kingdome, Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, firſt ſent two Legats into France, to trouble the ſtate, and to ſtirre vp tumults and ſeditions, and afterwards had ſo incited &amp; incenſed <hi>Otho</hi> the third, and <hi>Ferdinand</hi> Earle of Flanders, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the French, that they had at that time loſt their kingdom, if the two Princes afore-ſaid had not by their conſtancie hindered and withſtood the wicked imaginations &amp; plotts of the Pope. But what is this (ſay the reformed) to produce ſuch ancient Hiſtories conſidering that modern examples are yet freſh in euery mans memorie. The yeere 1585. Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fift, thundered &amp; lightened with his excommunication againſt <hi>Henry</hi> of Burbone king of France &amp; of Nauarre.<note place="margin">Brut. fulmen. Six. <hi>5.</hi> in regi. Gall. &amp; Nauar.</note> And againſt <hi>Henry</hi> of Burbone Prince of Condy: likewiſe againſt all their race and poſteritie, and hauing excommunicated them as heretikes did therewithall giue in pray all their countries and Cities.</p>
               <p>And that alſo which afterwards fell out is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently knowne to all, which is that the ſame Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the yere 1588. ſolemnly proclaimed the kingdome of England to be hereticall, and gaue the ſame to <hi>Philip</hi> king of Spaine: If we will alſo behold and conſider the perfidiouſnes or faithleſneſſe, and ſpirituall and Eccleſiaſticall diſloyaltie of Popes, we ſhal find in ancient Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that the Popes of Rome haue in all times contended among themſelues for the papall Chaire or dignitie. For <hi>Iohn</hi> the twentie foure,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:8263:23"/>
being come to Bolonia as Legate with many Souldiers,<note place="margin">The Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes of Popes.</note> much threatned all the Cardinals if they chuſe a Pope that were not to his liking, &amp; diuers being named and propounded, to none of which he would giue his conſent, at length hee was required, that himſelfe would ſignifie whom he would haue to be choſen: Then hee ſayd giue me this veſtment or attire of S. <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Popes chuſe themſelues. <hi>Stella venetus</hi>
                  </note> and I will deliuer it to him that ſhall be Pope, which being done he put it vpon himſelfe, and ſaid I am the Pope. And albeit this act greatly diſpleaſed all the other Cardinalls, they were notwithſtanding forced againſt their willes to yeeld conſent. In like manner <hi>Iohn</hi> the twentie two choſe himſelfe to be Pope when the electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was referred to him. The Reformed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſay moreouer that they can proue that the ſame time there haue been,<note place="margin">Foure, three and two Popes at the ſame time gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note> ſometimes foure, ſometimes three, ſometimes two Popes: For <hi>Victor, Alexander</hi> the third, <hi>Calixtus</hi> the third, and <hi>Paſchall</hi> had altogether at once the papall autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. In the time of the Emperour <hi>Fredericke Barbaroſſa,</hi> and <hi>Benedict</hi> the eight, <hi>Silueſter</hi> the ſecond, and <hi>Gregorie</hi> the fift, were Popes all at a time, vntill at the length <hi>Henry</hi> the third, Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour depoſed them.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe <hi>Gregorie</hi> the twelfth, <hi>Benedict</hi> the thirteenth, and <hi>Alexander</hi> did by excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions arrogate or obtaine the papall authoritie; all of them thundering their thunder-boults the ſame time. Moreouer diuers of them haue challenged the triple Crowne, and for the ſame
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:8263:23"/>
haue made warre one againſt the other. <hi>Stephen</hi> the third, againſt <hi>Conſtantine. Sergius</hi> the third, againſt <hi>Chriſtopher. Vrbane</hi> the fift, againſt <hi>Clement</hi> the ſeventh. <hi>Eugenius</hi> the fourth, againſt <hi>Clement</hi> the eight. And diuerſe other Popes (the menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning of which, would be too tedious and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome) haue done the like, as is verified by their owne Hiſtoriographers: Let euery man iudge then (ſay the Reformed) if theſe actes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue mentioned, may not rightly bee called perfidiousneſſe and ſedition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="reason">
               <head>Antichriſtianiſme the ſeventh cauſe of refuſall.</head>
               <p>In the ſeventh place,<note place="margin">The ſeventh reaſon.</note> the Popes cannot bee competent and ſufficient Iudges in the contro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verſie of Religion, for that (as the Reformed maintaine) the Popes themſelves were that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, which the holy Scripture teſtifieth to be the <hi>wicked one,</hi> the ſame childe of perdition,<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2. Apoc. 17. 1 Cor. 1.6. 2 Cor. 6. Epheſ. 2. 1 Tim. 4.</note> that <hi>oppoſeth and lifteth vp himſelfe againſt all which is called God: ſitting as God in the Temple of God: The whore that is drunke with the blood of the Saints; being ſeated vpon the Beaſt with ſeven heads, who committeth fornication with the Kings of the earth, and fighteth againſt the Lambe, by whom ſhee ſhall be ouercome:</hi> and finally, ſhall bee forſaken by ſeven hornes, or ſeven Kings. For ſince that the Popes attribute to themſelues more honour then to Ieſus Chriſt, and to the Magiſtrate, and ſo advance and lift vp themſelues aboue God. Behold the reaſon why they diſpence againſt the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:8263:24"/>
commandements of the Apoſtles; againſt right and the law of Nature,<note place="margin">Ten argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that the Pope is Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</note> that they place their acts aboue the iudgement of man; that they equall their ordinances to divine inſtitutions: That they attribute to themſelues the power of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring and changing of kingdomes; That they name themſelues head, ſpouſe, and high ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Prieſt or Biſhop of the Church;<note place="margin">The Heralds cry before the Pope, <hi>Abaſſo, Abaſſo,</hi> that is all downe on your knees. <hi>Diſt.</hi> 19. 11. 96. <hi>Bald. vlt. cap. Decius</hi> 1. <hi>de conſtit. Felin. c. eg.</hi> 1. <hi>de iure. Eber. Hardin. Anna. Iron.</hi>
                  </note> yea veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they terme themſelues the cauſe of cauſes, and the Lord of Lords: That they are ſeated in the Temple of God, being drunken with the blood of the Saints, poſſeſſing the Citie ſet vpon ſeven hils, which hath had ſoveraignty and rule ouer all the Kings of the earth. In briefe, ſeeing that all the things which haue beene foretold of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt in the holy Scripture, agree fitly, ſort rightly, and are proper to the Pope, we need ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect no other Antichriſt from <hi>Babylon.</hi> Beholde wherefore the Reformed conclude, from all the reaſons before going, that the Popes of Rome are the true Antichriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="reason">
               <head>The villanies of the Popes the eight cauſe of refuſall.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The eight reaſon.</note>In the eight place, the Reformed Chriſtians will not admit the Popes for their Iudges, for theſe their filthy vices and villanies enſuing.</p>
               <p>Firſt, they haue beene whoremongers. 2. Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants. 3. Poſſeſſed by Divels. 4. Atheiſts with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſence or feeling of God. 5. Tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors or bloody perſecuters. 6. Traytors. 7. Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners. 8. Baſtards. All the which things the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:8263:24"/>
Reformed ſay, they can ſufficiently proue true by the teſtimonies of ſuch Writers and Authors, being Papiſts, as in diverſe ages paſt haue written bookes thereof, which are at this day every where printed and ſet out, and conſequently may be read by every man.</p>
               <p>And firſt of all the Reformed prooue,<note place="margin">That the Popes haue been whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers and Sodomites.</note> that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe Popes haue beene Brokers, or Bawds, whoremongers, inceſtuous, and Sodomites. For <hi>Sergius</hi> the third committed filthineſſe with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Harlots, but eſpecially with <hi>Marozia</hi> that famous ſtrumpet, of whom hee begat Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> the twelfth. <hi>Landus</hi> the firſt, begat <hi>Iohn</hi> the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leventh in beaſtly whoredome. <hi>Iohn</hi> the eleuenth being heire to <hi>Landus</hi> the firſt, came alſo by right of whoredome to the Papall dignity, by the meanes of the Romane Courtezan <hi>Theodora,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luitpran. Firm. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi> De geſt imper. Patr. praem. &amp; Platin. Firm. l. <hi>2.13.</hi> Luitp. lib.</note> the which being often enflamed with the fire of luſt (I would ſpare or favour chaſte eares if I were not to expreſſe the very wordes of <hi>Luitprands</hi>) did not onely allure and provoke the Pope to vſe carnality with her, but did alſo ſometimes importune and compel him. <hi>Iohn</hi> the thirteenth,<note place="margin">Mantuan.</note> was conuinced at a Sinode in the preſence of the Emperour <hi>Otho</hi> the firſt, of diverſe notorious vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, among which, the principall was his hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible incontinency, which was that hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted inceſt with both his ſiſters, that hee had made a brothell-houſe of the Laterane Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, that hee had forced <hi>Stephana</hi> his fathers concubine, as alſo the widow <hi>Paniete,</hi> and <hi>Anne,</hi> together with his Neece: And being convinced
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:8263:25"/>
of all theſe villanous acts, hee was depoſed from the Papall throne, but the whores reſtored him againe, by a ſedition and mutiny that they rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed among the Nobility of Rome. <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt ſuffered <hi>Peter Mendoza</hi> Cardinall of Valence to abuſe his baſtard ſonne the Marquis of <hi>Zanete,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vates Volater.</note> as if he had beene his wife. And how much the ſaid Pope was tainted and polluted with luſtful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſufficiently appeareth by this Epitaph of his daughter <hi>Lucrece;</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>Hac iacet in tumba Lucrecia nomine; ſed re,</l>
                     <l>Thais, Alexandri filia, ſponſa nurus.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>That is to ſay;
<q>
                     <l>Here lies entomb'd Lucrece by name, but in her life</l>
                     <l>Alexanders daughter, daughter in law, and wife.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ioan, <hi>or</hi> Ione. Pont.</note>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> the eight, before called <hi>Gilberta,</hi> being got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with childe by a Cardinall, was delivered in a publike Proceſſion going towards the Church of Laterane, betweene the Colloſſe or Statue, and the Temple of Saint <hi>Clement;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Actus Sanara.</note> and that in the preſence of all the people, in the open ſtreet, in which place alſo ſhe died in labour, vpon which occaſion <hi>Baptiſt Mantuan</hi> compoſed theſe verſes enſuing:
<q>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">In Alphon. l. <hi>3.</hi> Platin. Funct.</note>Hic pendebat adhuc ſexum mentita virilem,</l>
                     <l>Foemina cui triplici Phrigiam diademate mitram</l>
                     <l>Extollebat apax &amp; pontificalis adulter.</l>
                     <l>Non poterat quiſquis deferrantes athere claues,</l>
                     <l>Non exploratis ſumere teſticulis,</l>
                     <l>Curigitur noſtro mus hic cum tempore ceſſat.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="41" facs="tcp:8263:25"/>Anne probat ſeſe quilibet eſſe marem.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>That is to ſay;
<q>
                     <l>Here was a Wench diſguiſ'd in mans attire,</l>
                     <l>to Popiſh triple Crowne that did aſpire:</l>
                     <l>Shee was with child, a Cardinall was the fire,</l>
                     <l>none afterwards might vſe heauens opening keyes.</l>
                     <l>Vnleſſe his markes of manhood were eſpied:</l>
                     <l>why ceaſeth then the cuſtome in our dayes?</l>
                     <l>Becauſe each Pope himſelfe a man hath tried.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>We reade that <hi>Iulius</hi> the ſecond beſides diuers others did principally ſpoyle by Sodomie two very yong noble Gentlemen which <hi>Anne</hi> queene of France,<note place="margin">Ian. Panop. Epiſt. Quin: qua eccleſia. Commenta. Mag Paris. Greuel George. Iuil.</note> had recommended and giuen in charge to <hi>Robert</hi> Cardinall of Nauetia, to traine them vp in good inſtructions. <hi>Innocent</hi> the third was ſo villanous a leacher that he abſtained not euen from the Cardinals; whoſe Sodomie hauing beene followed by <hi>Grouanni Delacaſa</hi> a Florentine, Archbiſhop of Beneuent,<note place="margin">The Booke was imprinted at Venice by <hi>Troy anq. Xanius.</hi>
                  </note> he wrote a a booke in Italian verſes in prayſe of Sodomie, which hee termeth <hi>diuinum opus,</hi> affirming that hee merited there by: <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth, ſet vp at Rome publike ſtewes and appointed them for fleſhly villaines, allowing to the Cardinal of Saint <hi>Lucie</hi> the act of Sodomie during the three hotteſt months of Summer; adding for the concluſion or ſhutting vp: <hi>Fiat quod petitur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iron Qucis. Ioan Rauis Bap. Man. lib. <hi>4.</hi> Alphons. Volat: in declam ad Leo.</note> that is, be it done that is required, or I grant thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt. <hi>Iohn</hi> the fourth, was depoſed from his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall ſeate at the Councell of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> becauſe of his Sodomie, rauiſhing of women, and ſuch
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:8263:26"/>
other enormious and haynous acts, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards detayned priſoner at Hedelberge for the ſpace of three yeeres.<note place="margin">Valer. Anctin. Vergarius. Agrippa.</note> 
                  <hi>Clement</hi> the eight, was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed in the declaration vpon the articles of the Maſters Sarboniſts of Paris, that he was the ſon of an Whore, an Enchanter, a Sodomite, a forcer of women, and a maſter of all abhomination: <hi>Paul</hi> the third, deliuered to <hi>Alexander</hi> one of his ſiſters againſt his wil, to be his Whore, to the end he might be made Cardinall of Heſtia. And the other ſiſter whom he had likewiſe defloured, hee cauſed to be made away by poyſon, becauſe he perceiued that ſhee did beare greater affection to others, then to himſelfe. The ſame Pope <hi>Paul</hi> committed filthines with his owne daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Conſtantia;</hi> and with his neece <hi>Laura Furnetia,</hi> and ſet downe in his regiſter, the number of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie fiue thouſand Whores from whom he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued monthly the reuenue or taxation impoſed for there vnchaſt conuerſation. Many more like examples (ſay the Reformed) of the Popes villanies might be alledged, but it is to be feared that the eares of well diſpoſed perſons would be thereby offended.<note place="margin">2. The tirannie and crueltie of Popes.</note> It remaineth therefore in the ſecond place for the Reformed to proue that the Popes haue beene cruell tyrants: <hi>Iohn</hi> the 13. cauſed the eyes of ſome of his Cardinalls to be put out,<note place="margin">Luitpran. lib. <hi>6.</hi> intog.</note> of others their tongues to be cut out, of others their noſes, and of others their priuie parts. <hi>Boniface</hi> the ſeuenth, cauſed <hi>Iohn</hi> the 13. by ambuſh or way-laying to be apprehended, and to haue his eyes put out, and ſuffering him
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:8263:26"/>
to die in priſon, by that meanes obtained the papall Chaire: <hi>Vrbane</hi> the ſixt chooſing new Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinalls cauſed 7. of the old ones to be caſt into priſon, fiue of which he commanded to be put into ſackes and caſt into the water. <hi>Innocent</hi> the eight of ſet purpoſe,<note place="margin">Valer. Anſel. Volateri marſil.</note> referred certaine Burgeſſes of Rome, who did exhort him to vnion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, to <hi>Lewis</hi> his nephew, reſiding or abiding in the Hoſpitall of the holy Ghoſt, where the ſaid Nephew hauing at the ſaid inſtant put to death two of them, he made them to be caſt out of the window, ſaying, that the diſcord and ſedition could not by a more conuenient means be pacified. <hi>Sergius</hi> the fift cauſed the body of <hi>Formoſus</hi> to be taken out of the graue, eight yeeres after he was dead, and made him to be placed on the papall ſeate where hee cauſed his head with three of his fingers to be cut off (the other two fingers hauing beene before cut off by <hi>Stephan</hi> the fift) and all this being further put in execution according to his pleaſure, hee further commanded to caſt the ſayd headleſſe bodie, together with the head and three fingers into Tiber. O rage and outragiouſneſſe neuer before herd of, ſay the Reformed.<note place="margin">3. That the Popes haue had acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with Diuels.</note> In the third place the Reformed Chriſtians doe declare the Popes haue beene poſſeſſed with Diuells, and haue familiaritie or commerce with euil ſpirits; For <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt, bound himſelfe by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract to the Diuell for his helpe and meanes to become Pope. <hi>Paul</hi> the third,<note place="margin">Brimo Cardinal. Luitpra. lib. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> was the cheefe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Negromancers: <hi>Benedict</hi> the ninth by
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:8263:27"/>
charmes called vp diuels into certaine woods, &amp; by diueliſh art or skill allured and entiſed into his armes all the women that he would. In the fourth place the Reformed ſhew that the Popes are prophane and Atheiſts.<note place="margin">4 That Popes haue beene Atheiſts.</note> For wee read that <hi>Leo</hi> the 10. on a day anſwered <hi>Petro Pembo</hi> who alledged ſome place of ſcripture: It is a good while ſince ſufficiently knowne,<note place="margin">Vita Pontif. Exempla Hul. &amp; Aug.</note> what profit and aduantage the fable of Chriſt hath brought to vs and to all our companie. <hi>Nicholas</hi> the firſt ſayd, that it was more honeſt and decent ſecretly to haue carnall copulation with many Whores,<note place="margin">Peter Prom. Ren: Cardi.</note> then openly before all men to liue with a wife in marriage. <hi>Silueſter</hi> the ſecond, one day ſaying Maſſe was ſo troubled with the noyſe of Diuells that with the very conceit and feare, he fell into a burning fever, and vnderſtanding the Diuell would haue him performe his promiſe, hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired vpon his death-bed, that after his death they would cut off his hands, and his tongue, &amp; his priuie parts. <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſeuenth, being in danger of death commanded that a certaine Cardinall ſhould be called vnto him,<note place="margin">Ben. Cardina.</note> to whom he himſelfe confeſſed that he was worthy to bee puniſhed with death, becauſe hee had amonge much people and many nations ſowed diſfenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; ſeditions, and had wrongfully perſecuted the Emperour <hi>Henry:</hi> Eating of Porke being by his Phyſitian forbidden to <hi>Iulius</hi> the ſecond, he ſpared not to vomit this blaſphemie,<note place="margin">Pantal. Paul. Verger.</note> in deſpite of God &amp;c. The ſame Pope <hi>Iulius</hi> being very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry for that a cold Peacock was eaten which he commanded
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:8263:27"/>
ſhould be ſaued or ſet vp: brake forth into another blaſphemy againſt the divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, and when one of the Cardinals ſitting at his table, ſaid vnto him, that his Holines ſhould not be ſo angry for a matter of ſo ſmall impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <hi>Iulius</hi> anſwered him; If God were ſo angry for the eating of an apple onely, that hee caſt our firſt parents out of Paradiſe, why ſhould it not be lawfull or allowable for me who am his Vicar, to be offended for a peacocke, ſeeing it is much more exquiſite &amp; pleaſing then an apple.</p>
               <p>In the fift place, the Reformed ſhew,<note place="margin">5. That the Popes are tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentors.</note> that the Popes are moſt cruell perſecuters, which they proue by the examples following: <hi>Iulius</hi> the 2. in the ſpace of ſeven yeeres,<note place="margin">Huld. Hut. <hi>See</hi> Gerbert. Gilb. Duth. Eraſm. Colet. Mattha. Pariſ.</note> cauſed more then two hundred thouſand to be murthered: <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> the ninth, cauſed to bee ſtrangled againſt all right the Ambaſſadours of the Emperour, by whom he vnderſtood, that <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was againe taken <hi>Clement</hi> the fourth, made publiquely to be beheaded <hi>Conradine,</hi> ſonne of the King of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilie,</hi> without any reaſon, or lawfull forme of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding. And what needeth it,<note place="margin">See the Booke of Martyrs.</note> ſay the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, to make here further mention of ſo many thouſand perſons, as the Popes haue cauſed cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly to be martyred in diuerſe parts of the world, and that onely for Religion.</p>
               <p>In the ſixt place,<note place="margin">6. The Popes are traitors.</note> the Reformed Chriſtians proue the treaſons of Popes by certaine notable examples; for to cite ſay they, all the examples would fill a great booke. The Emperour <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke</hi> made a publique complaint in the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:8263:28"/>
at <hi>Norenberch,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See how the Emperour was impriſoned &amp; releaſed by the Souldan.</note> of the treaſon of <hi>Alexander</hi> the third, and that in the preſence of the Princes of the Empire, cauſing openly to bee read before the ſaid Princes there aſſembled, his owne tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous letter which hee had ſent to the Souldan or Emperour of the Turkes: <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſecond made a ſecret prohibition of paying to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror his ordinary impoſt or cuſtomes. <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt, tooke and hyred the Turkes to ayd him againſt the French. <hi>Gregory</hi> the 9. requeſted the Souldan by letters, not to reſtore the holy Land, but rather to doe his beſt for the diſpatching of the Emperour.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">7. The Popes haue beene poyſoners.</note>In the ſeventh place, the Reformed prooue, Popes to haue beene poyſoners: And firſt of all Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the ſeventh, cauſed his owne mother and neece to be poyſoned,<note place="margin">Verger. Agap. Vicel. Volater. Mar. in Euſeb.</note> to the end that by this meanes all the hereditary goods of the Fornaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes might accrue or come vnto him. <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt, put to death by poyſon after the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh guiſe,<note place="margin">See <hi>Contaren. Verger,</hi> and other Authors</note> the brother of <hi>Gemene Baiezet,</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of the Turkes, and that againſt all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon right, and the law of Nations; for although hee were priſoner, yet the Turkes had before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand ranſomed and redeemed him for two ſums of gold. And as the ſaid Pope went about to do the like to certaine of his Cardinals,<note place="margin">Pet. de Viues lib. <hi>6.</hi> Epiſt.</note> the Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearer erred in the pots or flagons, &amp; having filled to him alſo ſome of the poyſoned wine, hee died together with the Cardinals that drunke there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, gaue poyſon to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour in the Hoſt, by meanes of a Prieſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:8263:28"/>In the eight place, the Reformed declare,<note place="margin">8. Popes haue been baſtards.</note> that the Popes for the moſt part haue beene baſtards and the ſonnes of whores: For <hi>Martin</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, was the ſonne of the prieſt <hi>Palumbus,</hi> a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gromancer, begotten on a whore. <hi>Iohn</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, was by whoredome the ſonne of Pope <hi>Landus</hi> the firſt. <hi>Sergius</hi> the third, did beget <hi>Iohn</hi> the twelfth of a famous ſtrumpet <hi>Marozia.</hi> Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Iohn</hi> the 12. had <hi>Iohn</hi> the 14. by a whore. Alſo the Prieſt <hi>Leo,</hi> begat <hi>Iohn</hi> the 16. <hi>Gregory</hi> the Biſhop, <hi>Benedict</hi> the 8. and <hi>Iohn</hi> the 22. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Laurence</hi> an Arch-prieſt, begot <hi>Sylveſter</hi> the third. <hi>Robert</hi> the Monke, <hi>Adrian</hi> the 4. <hi>Leo</hi> the 10. <hi>Clement</hi> the 8. <hi>Innocent</hi> the 3. <hi>Gregory</hi> the 9. <hi>Innocent</hi> the 4. <hi>Adrian</hi> the 5. So that all thoſe Popes before mentioned were begotten in villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous and ignominious whoredome.</p>
               <p>Finally,<note place="margin">Prodigies that fell out and came to paſſe by reaſon of the villanies of Popes, with ſtrange pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments for the ſame.</note> the Reformed produce alſo out of Hiſtories, many prodigies and wonders, or my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous ſignes and remarkeable puniſhments; by which the Almighty made it manifeſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that all thoſe villanies and filthy abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations aforeſaid of the Popes, did greatly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe him.</p>
               <p>And firſt of all concerning prodigies and ſtrange ſignes; It came to paſſe at <hi>Mapente,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sigebertus &amp; Vincentius.</note> in the time of Pope <hi>Benedict</hi> the third, that the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell hidden in the hood or coule of a Prieſt that gaue holy water, accuſed the ſayd Prieſt in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of all the people, to haue had carnall ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety the night before going, with the daughter of the chiefe officer. <hi>Benedict</hi> the ninth having
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:8263:29"/>
beene ſtrangled by the Divell, to whom he had abandoned and given himſelfe, there were ſeene at the ſame time great imfla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mations in the aire, in the ſhape of fiery houſes and beames. In the time of Pope <hi>Paſchall</hi> there fell out alſo diverſe and ſundry prodigies, and this eſpecially, that at <hi>Spire</hi> blood dropped out of certaine loaues of bread. When <hi>Lucus</hi> the third was Pope, who had allowed of, and countenanced the booke called <hi>Sacra Scortatorum,</hi> that is to ſay, the ſacred rite of Whore-maſters; there was a great earth quake which overthrew in <hi>Aſia</hi> many goodly Cities, &amp; in <hi>Sicilie</hi> deſtroyed 25000. per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. In the yeere 1224. when the Dominicans or Iacobins paſſed through <hi>Italie</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> prodigious tempeſts did ariſe, which overwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med many temples, buildings, and trees, there fell alſo haile-ſtones as bigge as an egge. When <hi>Vrbane</hi> the fourth was Pope, who ordayned the day of the Sacrament, commonly called Gods Feaſt, and that by the perſwaſion of a woman, there appeared in the ayre a great Comet for three months together,<note place="margin">Ioan. Novian. in illuſt. Batau.</note> the which after the ſame night that <hi>Vrbane</hi> died, appeared no more. <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas</hi> the firſt, begot of his concubine or whore, a childe that had haire and pawes like a Beare. <hi>Iohn</hi> the 24. having aſſembled a Synod at Rome, there to inveſt the King of Hungary, Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, after that the Maſſe of the holy Ghoſt was finiſhed, hee ſet him downe in his Papall chaire; at which very inſtant a hideous Owle flew to a beame right over againſt the Pope, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:8263:29"/>
hauing her eyes continually fixed vpon him, there ſate and cryed til the Pope with-drew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: and the ſecond Seſſion the ſame Owle came againe to the ſame place, and when they could not driue her away neither by noyſe, nor with cudgels, they were at length enforced to giue over, or breake vp the ſayd Synode, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having effected or concluded any thing. The day that <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth choſe thirty Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals a great tempeſt of thunder and lightening did ariſe after ſuch a manner, that the Chappell where the Ceremonies were performed with great ſolemnitie was ſtrucken therewith, and the ſame alſo plucked the Image of the little child Ieſus out of his mothers armes, &amp; the Keyes out of Saint <hi>Peters</hi> hands. Many other ſignes and prodiges haue come to paſſe, but the Reformed paſſing them ouer with ſilence comes to the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple proofe of certaine horrible puniſhments in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted from heauen vpon the grieuous ſinnes &amp; impieties of the Popes.<note place="margin">Maruelous puniſhments of the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Popes.</note> Pope <hi>Silueſter Campanus</hi> was baniſhed from Rome by the ſtrumpet <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore. Conſtantine</hi> the ſecond, was depriued at a Counſell of both his eyes,<note place="margin">See much of this in the life of the Popes deſcribed and ſet out by the author after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</note> as alſo of his Papall authoritie, and afterwards ſhut vp in a cloyſter. <hi>Adrian</hi> the fourth, flying from Rome came to Venice, in the attire of a Gardiner, where being hid in a couent hee was imployed in looking to the Garden. <hi>Adrian</hi> the fourth, was ſtrangled or choked with a flie that flew into his mouth. <hi>Iohn</hi> the twentie two, being cruſhed vnder with the fal of a vault of an houſe of pleaſure, ſo ended
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:8263:30"/>
his life. <hi>Iohn</hi> the eleuenth, impriſoned by the ſouldiers of Guydo, was ſtrangled with a pillow which they held hard or cloſe vpon his face; <hi>Benedict</hi> the ſixt, was by a Burges of Rome cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Cinthius</hi> ſhut vp in the Caſtle Saint <hi>Angeli;</hi> there by him ſtrangled for his enormious vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies. The bodie of <hi>Boniface</hi> the ſeuenth, who died ſuddenly was tied by the foote and thruſt through with pikes, and being drawne a long the ſtreets was ignominiouſly caſt into the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon place of buriall. <hi>Lucius</hi> the ſecond enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing to aſſault the Capitoll whether the chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors for their ſafetie were retired, was ſo ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly encountered and ſtrucken with blowes, that hee died verie ſhortly after. <hi>Innocent</hi> the fourth, hauing vniuſtly condemned to death <hi>Robert</hi> of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> becauſe hee had reprehended or taxed the horrible impieties of Popes, as well by word of mouth as by writing, the ſayd <hi>Robert</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing appealed to the Soueraigne Iudge Ieſus Chriſt, a voice was heard at the Popes ſeate cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Come wretched creature to the Iudgement of God. So that the next day the Pope was found dead vpon his bed, all his body being blacke and blew as if he had beene beaten, and bruſed with blowes of a cudgell. <hi>Nicholas</hi> the third died ſuddenly being ſtroken with an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexie. <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth died laughing and drinking roundly. <hi>Clement</hi> the eight, hauing conſpired with <hi>Francis</hi> king of France, againſt the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Charles</hi> the fift, was afterwards impriſoned by the Captaines of the Emperour and derided
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:8263:30"/>
after a ſtrange faſhion; and after, they had pilled or ſacked the Citie of Rome, he was reſtored to his pontificall authoritie but finally was ſtifled or ſmothered, with certaine Cardinals by the ſmoke of certaine Torches and waxen lights.</p>
               <p>Hitherto haue we vnderſtood the courſes &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons wherfore the Reformed Chriſtians will not accept the Popes for there Iudges in matter of religion. For they ſay in the firſt place, that it is repugnant to all lawes and rights both deuine and humane that in this cauſe or ſute Popes ſhould be both accuſers and Iudges. And that which is more according to the common Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and opinion of the Canoniſts, the Pope a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone cannot pronounce ſentence vpon an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie but muſt therein be Iudged alſo by others. Adding farther herevnto ſo many wicked acts of the Popes, whereof albeit they were not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted and condemned, but onely accuſed, yet ſo it is that they not only cannot be Iudges in religion; but are alſo incapable of accuſing the meaneſt perſon, before they haue ſufficiently purged and excuſed themſelues of all the before mentioned enormities. Finally for ſo much as this is agreeable to all naturall right and reaſon, that is to ſay that in all affaires and conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of importance, euery thing be reſolued vpon and concluded according to the opinion and ſentence of the greater and principall part; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when the greater part is eſteemed or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, not onely according to the number of perſons, but cheifly according to the nature,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:8263:31"/>
worthines and importance, of the whole affaire or matter, and goodneſſe of the cauſe. And Conſidering that all the Realmes and nations heretofore mentioned which accuſe the Popes doe largly extend and amount to the two principal parts of Chriſtendome; &amp; conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there remayning for the Romane Catholikes but one of the principall parts of Chriſtendome. The Reformed conclude that they may with all right &amp; reaſon reiect the Popes as incompetent and vnlawfull Iudges; wherefore (ſay the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) Let the Popes of Rome firſt and foremoſt purge themſelues of all the aforeſaid abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble acts and hainous villanies whereof they are accuſed, or elſe if they cannot doe it, let them forbeare to intrude themſelues, in quality or title of Iudges, touching the differences of Religion. Otherwiſe the Reformed ſay, that they ſhal haue iuſt occaſion to make that anſwere to Popes which was heretofore addreſſed or returned to Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> Biſhop by the Greeke Churches; the which Churches, the Pope had written vnto then, that he alone was the head of all the Churches, and the onely, and proper Vicar of Ieſus Chriſt, they anſwered him breefly in theſe termes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The letter of 7. Churches to the Pope.</note>
                  <hi>We firmely beleeue thy great authoritie ouer them that are ſubiect vnto thee, wee cannot endure thy great pride and ambition, wee cannot iuſtifie thy great couetouſnes. The diuel be with thee, for God is with vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Reformed come now to declare where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:8263:31"/>
and how farre forth they will not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Councells nor admit them for their Iudge. For they refuſe them as they ſay,<note place="margin">Why the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels are refuſed to be iudges in religion.</note> for diuers and ſundrie weightie reaſons. And firſt of all they affirme that there are diuers Councels which haue groſly erred, not onely in diſcipline and outward order, but alſo in that which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth the honour of our Saviour Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">The 1. reaſon of refuſall.</note> whence it hath come to paſſe, that oftentimes Provinciall Synodes haue beene corrected and controuled by Generall Councels, and Generall Councels by provinciall.</p>
               <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">The 2. reaſon of refuſall.</note> the principall and beſt Councels haue not alwayes treated of all the points and articles of Chrſtian Faith, but onely of certaine differences which were then moſt queſtioned.</p>
               <p>Moreover it appeareth by Hiſtories, that even <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> in the beſt golden ages, the pride and ambition, or the curioſity or impudence and indiſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or elſe the diſſoluteneſſe or evill carriage of certaine Biſhops and Paſtors hath beene ſuch, as it ſeemes that oft-times in the Councels and Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodes, the Spirit of God did not governe, but rather the vncleane ſpirit, who then prevailed &amp; got the vpper hand: In briefe, we reade that in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> theſe laſt ages ſuch Councels haue beene held, as haue brought in and confirmed falſe doctrine, and vnprofitable, frivolous and hurtfull ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies; and that not by arguments or reaſons, or by the authority of the Word of God, but rather by ſtrong force, &amp; by way of Armes. And to the end no man may think all this to be deviſed as a
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:8263:32"/>
falſe and malicious accuſation: the Reformed affirme, that they can plainely proue it by a briefe rehearſall and regiſter of the Councels; for who ſhall diligently ſearch into ancient and moderne Hiſtories, ſhall finde this to bee true, that even as following the ancient tradition of the houſe of <hi>Elias,</hi> all the time of the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of this world, is divided into thriſe three thouſand yeeres. In like manner all the time from the firſt comming of Ieſus Chriſt vntill his laſt comming at the day of iudgement may bee fitly diſtributed into three periods or parts, in which alſo all Realmes and Principalities haue felt ſome alteration and change. We finde alſo that in thoſe three periodes,<note place="margin">Three periods or partitions of Time of the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> or partitions of time, true Chriſtian religion and the vniverſall Church hath increaſed and decreaſed like the moone.</p>
               <p>For vntill about 500. yeeres after the birth of Chriſt, although that during the ſayd time, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine differences or controverſies did ariſe, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the perſon of the Sonne of God, and other very important points of religion, againſt <hi>Ebion, Cerinthus,</hi> and diverſe other Heretiques; yet the truth hath alwayes obtained the vpper hand: And during thoſe firſt fiue hundred yeeres, the Church of Chriſt flouriſhed, being as it were in full moone. For in this firſt period, were held the Apoſtolicall Councels; and afterwards all the foure Oecumenicall Councels, that is to ſay, vniuerſall of the Primitiue Church. And indeed the firſt of all thoſe Oecumenicall and Generall
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:8263:32"/>
was aſſembled or called at <hi>Nice</hi> by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great,<note place="margin">Con. Nice.</note> which confuted and condemned the wicked Heretique <hi>Arrius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond was aſſembled or held at <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> by the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Con. Conſt.</note> which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued and convinced the <hi>Macedonian</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques.</p>
               <p>The third was aſſembled in <hi>Epheſus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Con. Epheſ.</note> by the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> the ſecond ſonne of <hi>Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius,</hi> which condemned the Heretique <hi>Neſtorius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fourth was called and held in <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> by <hi>Marcion,</hi> and refuted and convinced the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retique <hi>Eutyches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Reformed proteſt,<note place="margin">Con. Chal.</note> that they will moſt willingly allow of the foure Creeds and Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Faith, ordayned by thoſe foure Generall Councels, as faithfull expoſitions of Chriſtian religion, for ſo much as they be grounded vpon the word of God.</p>
               <p>But in the 500 yeers enſuing,<note place="margin">The ſecond period of 500. yeeres.</note> falſhood ſo ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and encountered with the truth, that ſo ſoon as man began by little and little, to decline from the true and right rule of holy Scripture, there did forthwith ſpring vp diverſe plants of falſe doctrine, and of hurtfull ceremonies, which more and more encreaſed: for albeit, indeede in the fift Generall Councell called by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Iuſtinian,</hi> in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>5.</hi> Con. Gen.</note> all they were refuted which maintained that the bodie of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt was of immortall and incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible nature.</p>
               <p>Alſo howbeit, that at the ſixt generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:8263:33"/>
which was celebrated and held in the ſame place, by the authority of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the fifth, the Heretiques Monotholites were convinced and condemned. So it is that afterwards, and almoſt all the Councels enſuing, propounded and agreed vpon things altogether vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or for the moſt repugnant to the expreſſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> word of God. For in the ſeventh generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, which was firſt aſſembled by the Empreſſe of Conſtantinople, and from thence removed to Nice, it was held good and decreed, that Images ſhould be honoured and adored, the which was not delt in or determined by the authority of the word of God, but rather by the force of a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie army, for that purpoſe procured and called from <hi>Thracia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> The eight generall Councell was held in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> vnder the raigne of the Emperor <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilius,</hi> where Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> by his Legates com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to acknowledge the Church of Rome for the head of all other Churches, and that all lay and ſecular perſons ſhould be excluded from all election of Clerkes, or perſons Eccleſiaſtical, ſo that thereupon ſo great debate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention did ariſe betweene the Greeke and Latin Churches, concerning the primacy or chiefe, ſo that the controverſie is not at this day alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether determined and pacified.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The 3. period of 500. yeeres.</note>The other fiue hundred yeeres next follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſuch Councels and Synodes were held, as decreed almoſt nothing which was good, but rather pernicious doctrine was therein confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:8263:33"/>
and eſtabliſhed. For proofe whereof (ſay the Reformed) no more needs to bee done, but only to produce one Counſell of euery age be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned.</p>
               <p>In the Councell or Synod of Maience,<note place="margin">1049.</note> at which both the Emperour and the Pope were preſent together with an hundreth and thirtie Biſhops, the point touching the forbidding of marriage to Prieſts was diſcuſſed.</p>
               <p>In the Councell of Brixia which was aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled by the Emperour <hi>Henry Gregory</hi> the ſeuenth was depoſed from the papall ſeate,<note place="margin">1080.</note> by reaſon of his blaſphemies and villanies aboue mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <p>In the Councell of Pauiaohen when the Emp. <hi>Fredericke</hi> would haue had the election of the Popes reformed; a debate or ſtrife of 20.<note place="margin">1160.</note> yeeres continuance was ſtirred vp &amp; kindled which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured vntill the Pope had troden on the necke of the Emperour in the Citie of Venice.</p>
               <p>In the Councell of Lions,<note place="margin">1243.</note> 
                  <hi>Innocent</hi> the fourth made a decree againſt the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, and granted to the Cardinals power and leaue to weare red hats, and to ride on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe.</p>
               <p>In the Synode of Vienna in France,<note place="margin">1311.</note> 
                  <hi>Clement</hi> the fift ſolemnely pronounced his Clementines, and albeit that afterwards lying on his death-bed he commanded they ſhould be burned, becauſe he wel perceiued them to confirme diuers errors apt to entrappe or enſnare mens conſciences: This notwithſtanding his ſucceſſor <hi>Iohn</hi> the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:8263:34"/>
twentie three,<note place="margin">1414.</note> did againe appeare and ratifie the ſayd Clementines. The Emperour <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> cauſed a generall Councell to be ſummoned at Conſtance wherein Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> the twentie three was diſmiſſed of the papall ſeate, and <hi>Iohn Huſſe</hi> &amp; <hi>Hierome</hi> of Prage were condemned &amp; burned; becauſe they had embraced and followed the doctrine of <hi>Iohn Wicliffe</hi> an Engliſhman, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong diuers other points of good doctrine taught that the Supper of the Lord ought to be diſtributed to the people vnder both kinds with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the imagination and dreame of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation.</p>
               <p>In the time of the ſaid <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> there was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a Councell held at Baſil, where it was decreed that Popes ſhould be ſubiect to Councels, and becauſe this decree did greatly diſpleaſe Pope <hi>Eugenius,</hi> he cauſed the ſaid Councell to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued to Bolona, and from thence to Ferrara, and from thence againe to Florence. Finally <hi>Iulius</hi> the ſecond, aſſembled &amp; called the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Laterane, and Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the third, the Councell of Trent, but for ſo much as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in thoſe Councels were not according to the rules preſcribed in the word of God.</p>
               <p>The Reformed mainetaine that they are not any way obliged or tied to their decrees. So by that which is before alledged it manifeſtly appeareth (ſay the Reformed) what kind of Councells and Sinods haue beene held in thoſe laſt ages by them of the Romane Church.</p>
               <p>Now concerning the diuerſitie of repugnances
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:8263:34"/>
of Councells it is alſo eaſily to be diſcouered.<note place="margin">Repugnances of Councells.</note> For the Councell of Chalcedon condemned Eutiches, but the Councell of Epheſus did ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue and acquite him. The Councell of Nice condemned <hi>Arrius,</hi> but the Councells of Saricea, Smernia, and Millan maintained &amp; vpheld him.<note place="margin">Diſt. <hi>32.</hi> Con. praeter. hoſt.</note> The Councell of Numidia where Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> was preſident, would haue all thoſe rebaptized which were baptized by Heretikes; which the Councell of Carthage did abſolutely forbid.<note place="margin">Diſt. <hi>4.</hi> de Cons. con. Non. hoſt.</note> The Councell of Epheſus which was held in the time of Pope <hi>Celeſtine</hi> did permit to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate vnder both kinds,<note place="margin">Diſt. <hi>15.</hi> de Conſ.</note> but that of <hi>Conſtance</hi> in the time of <hi>Iohn</hi> the twenty three, and that of Lateran did rigorouſly forbid it.</p>
               <p>The Councell of Chalaus did ratifie offerings for the dead, that of Carthage reiected them. The Councell of Ancyra, &amp; of Nice, of Gangrae, of Coletan, and of Elibere, did all conſent to the marriage of Prieſts, and other Eccleſiaſticall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; but the Councells of Nerceſaria, and of Chalcedon, and of Agatha, and diuers other Councels did ſecretly forbid the ſame. The Councell of Toletua allowed Prieſts to keepe Concubines; but the Councell of <hi>Carthage</hi> and that of <hi>Baſill</hi> in the time of <hi>Eugenius</hi> the fourth, did ſharply forbid it.</p>
               <p>The Councell of Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> did forbid to heare Maſſe by a Prieſt that kept a Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine, which <hi>Lucius</hi> the third did permit. The Councell of <hi>Gangrets</hi> condemned all them that ordained or commanded new traditions to the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:8263:35"/>
people the which that of Conſtantinople did allow.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Diſt.</hi> 34.</note> The Councell of <hi>Tolete con.</hi> 2. and of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere con.</hi> 36. did reiect Images; but that of Nice the ſecond and diuers others did admit them. What would yee more. The Councell of Arminium denied the primacie of the Pope of Rome, but that of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> the ſixt and ſome others auerred and acknowledged it. The Councell of Gelaſe, decreed againſt Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation, contrariwiſe that of Florence in the time of <hi>Victor</hi> the ſecond, and that of Lateran in the time of <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, maintained &amp; ratified it. Conſider now well (ſay the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) of what force and authoritie Councels can be, and how litle they conſent and agree to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. So that for thoſe and ſuch like reaſons the Reformed will not accept or acknowledge the Councels for Iudges of the differences in Religion; but they wil admit them for witneſſes depoſed in this action or ſute, ſo far forth as their teſtimonies agree with the publike Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents or words of the teſtament, and with the words and meaning and intention of God our Soueraigne teſtator.</p>
               <p>As alſo S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> aduiſeth vs verie well, that is to ſay, that in differences of the Church we muſt neither follow the authoritie of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Epheſus, nor the Councell of Arminium, ſeeing we are not therevnto obliged, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that by the authoritie, and force of the holy Scripture we ſhould ſet and weigh cauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt cauſe, &amp; reaſon againſt reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Alſo that we
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:8263:35"/>
ought to giue more credite to a Lay-man who ſpeaketh the truth accoring to that which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in holy Scripture, then to a general Coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cel alledging falſhoods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the Scripture.</p>
               <p>Here now further followeth the third kinde of Iudges, that is to ſay, the ancient Fathers,<note place="margin">The ancient Fathers can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be Iudges in Religion.</note> which are alſo produced as Iudges of religion by them of the Church of Rome; but they of the Reformed Church will not admit them ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely for their Iudges. For firſt of all (ſay they) that there are very falſe doctors that are very ancient, and which is more, ancient Fathers haue alſo confeſſed of themſelues, that they might all erre and bee deceived. On the other ſide, becauſe that in the ages enſuing, the falſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion and peruerſe perſwaſion touching the invocation of Saints deceaſed, the too great ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration or reuerencing of Martyres, the alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goricall and too curious expoſition of holy Scripture, ſingle life or abſtinence from marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, Monkerie and Monaſticall or retyred kind of life, and the great number of ceremonies haue bin long ſince ſo deeply rooted, that euen ſome learned Doctors haue not onely endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſuppreſſe the aforeſayd errors, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, haue rather vpheld them, partly tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row couetouſneſſe, partly of ambition,<note place="margin">The faults &amp; errors of the Fathers.</note> partly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of ſet ſubtle purpoſe. The which the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſay, they can plainely proue by diuerſe and ſundry examples, but they ſuppoſe that thoſe enſuing will ſatisfie for this purpoſe.</p>
               <p>All Chriſtians acknowledge in the firſt place
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:8263:36"/>
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> for a good ancient Father and an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupt and Orthodoxe Doctor,<note place="margin">Tertullian.</note> ſo farre forth that he confuted by the written word of God the Heretiques <hi>Marcion</hi> and <hi>Praxias,</hi> both which denied the divine and humane nature of Ieſus Chriſt: but for ſo much that he maintaineth the error of the <hi>Chilliaſts,</hi> and diſalloweth of ſecond mariages, all Chriſtians muſt confeſſe he erred.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Cipryan.</note>
                  <hi>Cyprian</hi> held very true opinions of the holy Trinity, of the Baptiſme of little children; and of the right vſage of the holy Supper; yet here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in alſo hath he failed, that is to ſay; That hee holdeth that ſuch ſhould bee baptized againe, as were formerly baptized with Heretiques, that hee too exceſſiuely praiſeth ſingle life, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaining from marriage.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ambroſe.</note>Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> hath written diverſe godly bookes of the holy Trinity, and of the doctrine of Iuſtification; but the ſubborned or ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed books in our time publiſhed vnder his name, are refuſed by the Reformed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hierome.</note>
                  <hi>Hierome</hi> hath greatly edified the Chriſtian Church by his writings, wherein hee teacheth that the true regeneration or renewing of man, proceedeth not from the power and naturall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of free-will: but hee greatly over-ſhoots &amp; denies himſelfe when he ſo much diſeſteemes and diſgraceth the ſtate of marriage, as to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce her a whore that after her firſt marriage marrieth againe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note>Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> being the moſt vncorrupt Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of all the ancient Fathers; hath in truth
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:8263:36"/>
done great ſervice to the Church of Ieſus Chriſt, when hee fundamentally by the Word of God confuted the <hi>Arrians,</hi> the <hi>Manicheans,</hi> the <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> and the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> but for ſo much as <hi>manet hoc,</hi> that children ſhould receiue the Lords Supper, herein hee did not ſufficiently conſult with the Word of God.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Gregorie</hi> held a good opinion,<note place="margin">Gregorie.</note> in ſaying that hee was Antichriſt who cauſed himſelfe to be called ſupreame and vniverſall Biſhop, yet did hee greatly erre in forbidding and infringing the lawfull marriage of Paſtors and Miniſters of Gods Word; when he thus writeth; That it is by no meanes lawfull to renounce or giue ouer a monaſticall life, and when hee is ſo carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with apparitions, ſpirits and, viſions, that hee is abſolutely repugnant to the Word of God.</p>
               <p>Furthermore how (ſay the Reformed) can we ſimply accept of the ancient Fathers fully and wholly for our Iudges,<note place="margin">Sentences and teſtimonies of the Fathers contrary to the doctrine of the Church of Rome. <hi>Ambroſius.</hi>
                  </note> conſidering that our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers the Popes themſelues, doe not allow and admit all the ſentences &amp; teſtimonies of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Fathers. S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, that for honeſty ſake and for ſeemly reſpect vnto the dead, they ſhould be ſuffred to remain at reſt in their graues.<note place="margin">Gelaſius l. <hi>1.</hi> de Aba. in Con. Re.</note> 
                  <hi>Gelaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> ſaith, that the ſubſtance or eſſence of Bread &amp; Wine in the holy Supper remaineth inſeparable, even as in our Saviour Chriſt the humane nature abideth vnited with his owne nature.<note place="margin">Aug. l. <hi>2.</hi> per. morit. cap. vlt.</note> Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> ſaith, that it is preſumption to conclude or determine any thing on any ſide in divine
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:8263:37"/>
things which are obſcure, without cleere and manifeſt teſtimonies of holy Scripture.<note place="margin">Calix. diſt. <hi>6.</hi> de Con.</note> 
                  <hi>Calixtus</hi> diſtributed the Sacrament of the holy Supper to all the Church, and debarred from it diſſolute perſons, and excommunicated all them which being preſent in the aſſemblie received not for all that the ſupper of the Lord.<note place="margin">Cyp. l. <hi>1</hi> epiſt. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſayd, that the blood of the Lord ought not to bee denyed to Chriſtians, for the confeſſion whereof they are bound to ſhead their blood. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi> taxed <hi>Minta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>us</hi> with this hereſie among others,<note place="margin">Apol eccl. hiſt. lib. <hi>5</hi> cap. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> to haue beene the firſt that had inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted certaine lawes and ordinances concerning faſting.<note place="margin">Paph. hiſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Paphnutius</hi> maintained that marriage ſhould not bee forbidden to Prieſts or Paſtors of the Church, declaring that the company with a mans owne wife is chaſtitie.<note place="margin">Cyp. l. <hi>1</hi> epiſt. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that the Lord Ieſus alone is to be hearke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto concerning whom it is pronounced or commanded, heare him. Alſo, that we muſt not regard what they which haue beene before vs haue ſaid or done; but what Chriſt who is before all hath commanded. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, that the Chriſtian Church ſhould not lift it ſelfe vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue Chriſt,<note place="margin">Aug. con. Croſc. cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> becauſe hee iudged alwaies truely and rightfully; but Eccleſiaſticall Iudges often faile and fall into error.<note place="margin">Amb. lib <hi>2.</hi> de Offi. cap. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note> Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, that religion and divine ſervice requires neither gold nor ſilver, and alſo that by gold we haue not the fruition of thoſe things which cannot be bought for gold. <hi>Spirdion</hi> ſaith, that hee did freely eate fleſh vpon ſuch dayes as others did abſtaine from
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:8263:37"/>
it, becauſe he was a Chriſtian:<note place="margin">Aug. ſuper meno. reap. <hi>17.</hi> Epiphanius.</note> 
                  <hi>Auſtine</hi> writeth that Monkes ſhuld not liue on other mens goods, although they were continually occupied in ſpeculations or contemplations, in praying &amp; ſtudying: <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſaith that it is a ſhamefull and vile thing to ſee in the Churches of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians any Images painted, or reſemblance of Chriſt, or any other he or ſhee Saint.</p>
               <p>Now then forſomuch as the Church of Rome it ſelfe tranſgreſſeth and paſſeth ouer ſuch and like ſentences, and maximes of the ancient fathers and doctors; I pray you with what right (ſay the Reformed) can it preſcribe to others to obſerue fullie and wholie that which it ſelfe leaues vndone and vnregarded.</p>
               <p>And ſince that neither Popes nor Councells nor fathers can in any ſort decide this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie and difference in religion,<note place="margin">That traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons cannot be Iudges in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</note> to whoſe Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then muſt wee referre and yeelde our ſelues? Muſt we relie vpon Traditions? By Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions muſt be neceſſarilie vnderſtood either <hi>Ritus,</hi> the <hi>rites,</hi> the ordinarie vſages or Cuſtomes of the Church:<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. <hi>3.</hi> hiſt cap. <hi>4.</hi> lib. <hi>5</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi> Irenaeus. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>14.</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>13.12.</hi> Tertull in prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript. ad haereſ.</note> or elſe Chriſtian doctrine it ſelfe. Concerning vſages or cuſtomes Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall, how ancient ſoeuer they may be, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſo far forth as they are either hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or improfitable or repugnant to the word of God, or haue beene heretofore abrogated or diſanulled they ſhould by no meanes bee tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, much leſſe entertained or obſerued in the Chriſtian Church. For the Lord expreſly forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to ſerue or honour him with a doctrine for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:8263:38"/>
or deuiſed out of mans braine or fancie.<note place="margin">Tertull in prae. fat. hereſ.</note> And concerning Traditions which concerne doctrine they muſt neceſſarily containe either the written word of God, or the words and expoſitions of the faith againſt Heretikes which by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence are drawne and fetched from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the holy Scripture; or elſe Traditions of doctrine comprehend and containe things ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther added or diminiſhed and taken away from the written word of God; be it apparently done or couertly.</p>
               <p>When by Traditions the written word of God is vnderſtood, or the Creede and Orthodoxe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of Chriſtian faith, who would not moſt readily, and willingly embrace &amp; allow ſuch Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions? But if by traditions be meant things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented and deuiſed beſide and againſt the word God, who would not ſet light by and reiect them that is deſirous to keepe a good and ſound con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience before God? Moreouer what vertue and authoritie, Traditions can haue to ſuppreſſe or appeaſe the debate and differences about Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, auncient Hiſtories doe ſufficiently certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie.<note place="margin">Aug. ad Laſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam Epiſt. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> For whereas in times paſt a great contention did ariſe in the Church about the feaſt of Eaſter, and that ſuch a ſtirre and contention, that almoſt all the world was there with diſquieted. Both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke themſelues for their refuge to the Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which are called Apoſtolicall, which are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther written nor contained in any certaine booke; and whereas either partie maintained that they obſerued the feaſt of Eaſter at the ſame
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:8263:38"/>
verie time which was ordained and ſet downe by the Apoſtles, at length the matter came to this point,<note place="margin">Irenaeus Epiſt. vit. Epiſt. Rom. Aug lib de vera religo.</note> that in ſuch &amp; the like indifferent things the Chriſtian Churches ſhould be left to their libertie. So that by this example it manifeſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, how weake humane traditions are to remoue and determine differences in religion.</p>
               <p>Shall they then be miracles which muſt giue vs to vnderſtand who follow the better partie,<note place="margin">That miracles cannot be true workes of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</note> and which is the true Catholike Church. It is impoſſible (ſay the Reformed) becauſe the end or purpoſe and gift it ſelfe of miracles now cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. For in theſe dayes no new Goſpell or ſtrange doctrine is Preached in the Chriſtian Church, which hath neede to be confirmed by miracles, but the ſame doctrine is taught which our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and his Apoſtles haue long ſince ſufficiently confirmed and ſeated by their miracles.</p>
               <p>Moreouer we doe not reade that all ſuch as haue heretofore reformed Religion and diuine ſeruice haue done miracles. In which ranke and number wee may reckon and place <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> vnder the new Teſtament, and vnder the old teſtament, <hi>Aſaph, Ethan, Iedithem, Iliman, Core,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Chron. 22.30. Ierom. 10.35. &amp; 8.16.</note> and certaine Prophets. And if the gift of doing miracles be not referred to the onely and wiſe gouernement and guiding of God, miracles can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not confirme any doctrine: It being verie cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that euen the miracles of Ieſus Chriſt, as excellent and full of efficacie as they were,<note place="margin">Luk. 11.19.</note> did not helpe forward the obſtinate Iewes towards
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:8263:39"/>
Chriſtian faith and true pietie:<note place="margin">Ioh. 12.26. 2 Theſ. 2. Deut. 13.</note> Finally, how (ſay the Reformed) ſhuld miracles in themſelues and of themſelues be neceſſarie markes or to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of true religion; ſeeing it is moſt euident that Antichriſt himſelfe, and the falſe Prophets haue ſhewed and done many ſignes and mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and ſo may doe in time to come. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Reformed affirme, that all ſuch as at theſe dayes require miracles, ſhould be them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues eſteemed maruilous men and ſtrange mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, ſeeing that they relie ſo much vpon mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, after that the gift of them haue long agoe ceaſed. Howbeit for all that we cannot, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it a kind of miracle that true Religion &amp; Chriſtian doctrine, ſhould be Preached and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced or ſet vp without miracles, among ſuch reſiſtances and furious endeuours of Antichriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">That the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Popes &amp; Biſhops can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be Iudges of true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</note>Shall it be then the continuall ſucceſſion of the Biſhop of Rome, that muſt diſtinguiſh the true Religion from the falſe? No man ſurely can denie, but that there is a ſucceſſion of true doctrine, and a ſucceſſion perſonall, of perſons only; and therefore the Reformed maintaine, that when ſucceſſion of perſons is accompanied with the ſucceſſion of true doctrine Prophetical and Apoſtolicall, that then without all doubt, ſuch a ſucceſſion is of great efficacie. And in this ſenſe and meaning it is, that heretofore all the Orthodoxe doctors of the Chriſtian Church oppoſed their ſucceſſions againſt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes. For he that maketh profeſſion of a doctrine (thoſe are the words of <hi>Nazianzen</hi>) is alſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:8263:39"/>
of the the ſame Throne, Chaire, or State; but he that embraceth contrary doctrines, ſuch an one ſhall not be accounted as a true ſucceſſor. And this ſecond hath the name and title, but the firſt hath true effect of ſucceſſion, without which ſucceſſion is but a bare following of one thing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another, when the diſeaſe is ſaid to ſucceed or follow after health, darknes after light, tempeſts after calme, folly and raſhneſſe after wiſedome and prudence, lees or dregs after wine or beere:<note place="margin">Hitherto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the words of <hi>Nazianzen.</hi>
                  </note> Alſo as we ſay, that <hi>Nero</hi> ſucceeded <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> and <hi>Cambyſes Cyrus:</hi> Conſidering then, that the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the Propheticall and Apoſtolicall doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine hath long ſince ceaſed in the Church of Rome, the Reformed conclude, that the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſucceſſion of the Popes of Rome, and of the Biſhops of the Romane Church, is not ſufficient to eſtabliſh true religion,<note place="margin">When the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine ceaſed in the Romane Church.</note> nor in any ſort thereof to determine.</p>
               <p>But it may be they of the Romane Church, will demand of the Reformed Chriſtians, at what time, and vnder what Pope the ſucceſſion of true doctrine was interrupted, changed, and altered? To which the Reformed anſwer; that the Popes and Biſhops of Rome muſt be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed and divided into three ranks or ſorts: For firſt all, the Reformed deny not,<note place="margin">The firſt ranke of Romane Biſhops.</note> but that from <hi>Linus</hi> to <hi>Melchiades,</hi> the firſt Biſhoppes of Rome (being thirty and one in number) were faithfull Paſtors of the Church of Chriſt, who laboured in the vineyard and harveſt of the Lord even vnto death; and therefore they may right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be called ſtarres, remayning in the right hand
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:8263:40"/>
of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: but from <hi>Sylveſter</hi> the firſt,<note place="margin">The ſecond ſort of Popes.</note> to <hi>Sabian</hi> the <hi>Thuſcan</hi> (thirty three in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) they (ſay the Reformed) were but Biſhops with Miters, which albeit they were not the worſt, did notwithſtanding by their traditions and decrees, prepare the ſtate and throne for the great Antichriſt. All the other Popes from him vnto the Pope at this preſent,<note place="margin">The third ſort of Popes.</note> are called and held by the Reformed for Antichriſts, in ſuch ſort notwithſtanding, as that the firſt of thoſe Popes vnto twenty and nine after <hi>Boniface</hi> the fift, and <hi>Leo</hi> the fourth, are accounted to be in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the great Beaſt: the other thirty and one Popes enſuing from <hi>Iohn</hi> the eight vnto <hi>Iohn</hi> the ſeuenteenth are regiſtred and recounted in the kingdome of the great Whore:<note place="margin">Apoc. 17.</note> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nine and thirty Popes ſucceding vnto <hi>Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> the fourth,<note place="margin">Apoc. 17. Apoc. 20. Apoc 9.</note> belong to the kingdome of the great Dragon: and all the laſt Popes from <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> the fourth, vnto the preſent Pope, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth the number of fiftie, are enrowled or numbred in the kingdome of Graſhoppers, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ancient propheſie, which the Lord hath vouchſafed to reveale vnto vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the kingdome of Antichriſt. Beholde how plainely it appeareth (ſay the Reformed) that the perſonall ſucceſſion of Biſhops is of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſmal importance and authority to decide the difference of religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The conſent and accord in the outward ſervice cannot be a marke of true religion.</note>But yet (ſay they of the Roman Church) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not the vnion, good agreement, and conſent in publique doctrine and outward ſervice demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:8263:40"/>
which is the true Catholique Church.</p>
               <p>To which the Reformed reply, that if bare conſent and accord in outward ſervice could performe ſo much, that then neither the Iewes, nor the Turkes, nor any other Heretiques, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans and Infidels, could bee excluded from the Catholique Church; for as much as experience in all times doth ſufficiently proue them marve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly to agree, and to be of one iudgement and conſent in their perverſe hereſies and falſe errors. whereas contrariwiſe, wee ſee often-times great and excellent Orthodoxe Doctors,<note place="margin">Diſſention of diverſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Doctors. Act. 15.</note> to haue had ſharpe and bitter diſſention and contention one with the other. Betweene <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> ſuch ſtrife was ſtirred and kindled, that one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from the other; euen ſo <hi>Peter Alexandrine</hi> and <hi>Melitus</hi> did ſtriue and contend each againſt other; as alſo <hi>Epiphanius</hi> and Saint <hi>Cryſoſtome;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Soz. l. <hi>1</hi> c. <hi>16.</hi> Socr. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>32.</hi> Orig. con. Celſ. lib. <hi>7.</hi> Srom. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> Saint <hi>Ierome,</hi> and Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Ruffin:</hi> likewiſe <hi>Ciril, Iohn</hi> of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and <hi>Theodoret.</hi> Yea pagan Infidels haue often vpbraided and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Chriſtians, for their diſagreement and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union: Whence it appeareth more cleere then the Sun at noone-day (ſay the Reformed) that as externall agreement, or the onely vnion and conſent in the outward ſervice of God, cannot decide or determine of the truth of religion; ſo on the contrary part alſo, every kinde of diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and partaking is not by and by a token or marke of falſe religion. Yet with this <hi>proviſo</hi> or <hi>caution,</hi> that the foundation of the truth be not ſubverted by the debate and difference in the diſſention.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:8263:41"/>
                  <note place="margin">That the moſt ancient cuſtom is not a marke of the true Church.</note>Shall it be then the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon &amp; publike cuſtom of diverſe ages that can ſhew vs where we muſt ſeeke and find the true Church? The Reformed anſwer, that as the eternall God hath expreſly forbidden the faithfull to permit and ſuffer his eternal and divine truth in any ſort to be impay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, defaced, or diminiſhed, either becauſe of time, or proſcription of many yeeres, or by any cuſtome bee it never ſo ancient<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or by any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring and generall aſſent whatſoever, yea al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it were of the whole world. So that wee ſee that the good Patriarch <hi>Noe</hi> with all his familie,<note place="margin">Gen. 7. Heb. 11.</note> although hee ſaw all men to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire and conſent together in impiety, and diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute life, it being growne to a cuſtome in certaine ages afore-going, hee notwithſtanding did ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther embrace with thoſe of his familie divine doctrine, then conſent with all other to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety and prophanation of the whole world; Muſt it then bee the Church that ought to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and compound all theſe grear controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies in religion? The Reformed ſay, that firſt and foremoſt we muſt learne well to diſtinguiſh the true Church from the falſe Synagogue and the aſſembly of the vngodly;<note place="margin">That the only written Word of God ſhould be Iudge of religion.</note> which cannot be effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by any other meanes then by the only writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Word of God. Muſt then the holy Scripture be full and ſole, or competent Iudge of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference and ſtate depending betweene theſe diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing and divided inheritors? The Reformed Chriſtians are altogether of this opinion, and thereupon are fully reſolved.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:8263:41"/>For indeed they maintaine and certainely ſhew with S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> S. <hi>Ciprian,</hi> and diuers other very ancient fathers and Orthodox doctors, that the things which are neceſſarie to the ſaluation of the faithfull, and children of God,<note place="margin">Luk. 16. Io. 4. Io. 6. Io. 15. Act. 28. Pro. 30. 2 Tim. 3. Eſa. 8.</note> are all exactly contained in the written word of God which is commonly called the holy Scripture. For Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> verie well ſaith.<note place="margin">Aug. tract. in Iohan. ca. <hi>11.</hi> Chryſoſt. hom. <hi>41.</hi> c. <hi>22.</hi> in Ioh.</note> It is only to the bookes of holy Scripture now called Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall that wee muſt attribute and giue this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and reuerence firmely to beleeue that none of their authors haue tripped or erred in their writings: But concerning other writers and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors we reade them in ſuch manner, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they haue beene verie holy and Godly and of much knowledge, yet ſo it is that wee hold not, what they haue written for true only becauſe they taught this or that; but becauſe they haue beene able to perſwade, and to make vs vnderſtand it ſo to be, either by thoſe Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call writings or by ſome other reaſons, which in ſubſtance agree with the truth and word of God. So that wee owe this onely to the Canonicall Bookes (as Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſaith elswhere) that is to ſubmit our ſelues to them without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction.<note place="margin">Lib. de na. &amp; gra. cap. <hi>6.</hi> Con. Fauſt. lib. cap. <hi>5.</hi> ad Oroſ. cap. <hi>11.</hi> ad Pan. ad Fortu. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Con.</note> Moreouer it may be lawfull to refuſe any other writtings, and to varie from them in opinion, but all perſons muſt yeeld conſent to the Canonicall writings be he Laicke, be he Prieſt, be he King, be he Emperour, let him giue heede and attention to the holy Scripture, for in the whole world nothing can be found ſo holy,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:8263:42"/>
and ſo neceſſarie as the holy Scripture.<note place="margin">Creſcon. gram. cap. <hi>32.</hi> Ad Vnam Don: Epſt. <hi>4.8.</hi>
                  </note> What I pray you can be found or met with all more cleare and euident, then all thoſe excellent teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and ſentences of Saint <hi>Auſtine.</hi> And in truth, ſay the Reformed, if we could once come to this point that God himſelfe might be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged to be Iudge of all differences in Religion, and that by his voice which clearely ſoundeth and vttereth it ſelfe in the writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles, we would not refuſe likewiſe to accept and allow the Councells, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and Miracles, and ſuch like for depoſed witneſſes in this cauſe or action. Prouided al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, that firſt of all diſtinction be diſcreetly and conſiderately made between the true Church, which is the aſſembly of Ieſus Chriſt, and the Sinagogue, and aſſembly of Sathan; betweene the auncient fathers and Orthodoxe doctors worthy of creedit; and Heretikes; betweene the lawfull Councels and Synods; and Tirannicall Councels &amp; Sinods; betweene the true writings of Orthodoxe men; and baſtard bookes or ſuborned writings; betweene true miracles, and and counterfeit ones: betweene rightfull ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of true Doctrine, and the diſguiſed ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of perſons; betweene true conſent and holy Vnion, and peruerſe and obſtinate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plotting and agreement in opinion. Briefly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the true Traditions of the Apoſtles, and the falſe gloſſes or expoſitions of men: Herevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to replie they of the Romiſh Church and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand how all this can be effected by the written
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:8263:42"/>
word of God, ſeeing that in like manner all Heretikes defend arme or ſtrengthen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with this written word of God. The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed anſwere,<note place="margin">How the Scripture may be iudge albeit all Heritekes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe it.</note> that Heretikes cannot more conueniently and fitly be confuted and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced (which abuſe this holy Scripture) then by the ſame written word of God, the which on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and alone can ſuppreſſe and determine all controuerſies in religion;<note place="margin">Ad Creſum lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>31.</hi>
                  </note> for as Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> verie well ſaith, we muſt by no meanes Iudge or controule the bookes of the Prophets and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, but we ought rather according to thoſe bookes to Iudge of all other bookes of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous profeſſors, or of Infidels. Euen ſo we ſee that our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt confuted and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded by the holy Scripture,<note place="margin">Mat. 12. &amp; 4.</note> the Scribes Phariſes and Sadduces, yea Sathan himſelfe all which abuſed the Scriptures; So likewiſe Saint <hi>Stephen</hi> conuinced the Iewes, and <hi>Philip</hi> conuerted the Eunuch of Queene Candace by the holy Scriptures.<note place="margin">Act. 6.7.</note> In like manner did the Apoſtles confirme the doctrine of the Goſpell by the writings of the Prophets. And the Iewes of <hi>Beraea</hi> compared the Preaching and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> with the doctrine of the Prophets, by this meanes trying whether it agreed with the writings of the Prophets.</p>
               <p>In ſumme after the ſame manner the Councell of <hi>Nice</hi> condemned the Heretike <hi>Arrius;</hi> that of Conſtantinople the Heretike <hi>Macedonius;</hi> that of <hi>Epheſus Neſtorius;</hi> that of <hi>Chalcedon Euti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches;</hi> that is to ſay by the onely word of God.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:8263:43"/>
Even as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> alſo convinced the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retique <hi>Pelagius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. de con ſen. Epiſt. <hi>163.</hi> lib <hi>3.</hi> Con ca. <hi>6.</hi> Sozom. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>Tertullian</hi> the Heretique <hi>Drapeas:</hi> Briefly all the other faithfull Doctors haue ſo reſiſted (that is) by the holy Scripture all Heretiques.<note place="margin">Theſe are the very words of Saint <hi>Auſten lib</hi> 2 <hi>cap</hi> 32. <hi>contr. Creſc.</hi>
                  </note> Wherefore as (Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> very well ſaith) Let no man in diſputations pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly obiect or oppoſe againſt vs the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the ancient Fathers or Councels, for we hold them, not in themſelues Canonicall, but doe examine them by the Canonicall writings; and whatſoever agreeth with the authority and excellency of the holy Scripture, wee accept of with commendation; but that which accordeth not therewith, wee reiect it with their leaue and conſent.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">That the Scripture is neither hard nor obſcure.</note>If they of the Romane Church reply, that the holy Scripture is obſcure, and hard to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood,: Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> anſwereth them, that wee more certainely wade or paſſe through the holy Scripture, then through Traditions. For when we will diligently ſearch into it, being dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened with ſome obſcure words, nothing wil en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue that can breed any difficulty, or if there doe ariſe any difference or doubtfulneſſe, it muſt be at length cleared and decided by ſundry more plaine teſtimonies of the ſame Scripture. And indeed (as the ſame ancient Father ſaith) the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt hath ſo tempered and compoſed the Scripture, that whatſoever ſeemeth obſcure in one paſſage, is more cleerly expounded in ſome other. Wherefore the Reformed conclude, for all the reaſons afore-ſaide, that this is the only
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:8263:43"/>
meanes, powerfull to ſatisfie and appeaſe thoſe two pretending or contending parties; that is to ſay, if endeavour be vſed to ſuppreſſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide by the pure Word of God the controverſies aboue mentioned, adiudging that alone to bee the true religion and Catholike Church, which agreeth fully and wholy with the Word of God, rightly expounded, and vnderſtood according to the ſame Word of God, and the Analogie of the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith.<note place="margin">The exception of the Church of Rome.</note> They of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Church pondering theſe reaſons of the Reformed Chriſtians, doe proteſt, that albeit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they well perceiue the religion of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed not much to decline from the written Word of God, and if it wholly accord with the the ſame, that yet they would not hold and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the ſame Reformed religion to be good, becauſe (ſay they) the ſayd Reformed religion was firſt ſet on foot and publiſhed by Heretikes, and Doctors that were not ſent by God, nor had a lawfull calling, and who were innovators and new deviſors in religion.<note place="margin">The anſwer of the Reformed.</note> The Reformed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians doe earneſtly entreat, that they of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Church would not accuſe them of ſuch faults, that is to ſay, of hereſie, vnlawfull calling, and innovation or bringing in of novelties; but rather perceiving their religion to conſent and accord with the truth of God, contained in the writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles, that they would imbrace the Reformed religion. For firſt of all the Reformed Chriſtians complaine very much of the wrong that is offered them, in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vſing
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:8263:44"/>
their religion of hereſie,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. de Har. <hi>2.</hi> Man Ioan. Auent. lib. <hi>3.</hi> Annal.</note> becauſe they can proue that ſuch are not Heretiques, as in ſome points diſſent from the opinion of the Romane Church, neither they which maintain that there are Antipodes,<note place="margin">Antipodes are they which tread againſt our feet. <hi>Gloſ. diſt.</hi> 10. <hi>ca. Mul. diſt.</hi> 2. <hi>Euſeb. l.</hi> 5 <hi>c</hi> 26. <hi>Lib. confeſ fol.</hi> 274. 6. 4. <hi>Ar. Flor. hiſt. par.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 13.</note> as Pope <hi>Zacharie</hi> did thinke; nor all they which will not obey all the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and ordinances of the Pope, as the Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts haue determined; nor they which giue not conſent to the celebrating of Eaſter, as Pope <hi>Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> appointed; neither they which beleeue not all the traditions which are inſtituted &amp; obſerved as good and godly by the Romane Church: For then all ſuch ſhould be heretiques as beleeue not that <hi>Dominick</hi> wrought more miracles then our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and all the Apoſtles: Alſo that the ſaid <hi>Dominick</hi> is greater then <hi>Ioh. Baptiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, that we muſt firmely beleeue all the Legends of Saint <hi>Francis, Bernardine,</hi> and other ſuch like, vnder paine and penaltie of being damned, excommunicated and burned as Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques. To conclude, all thoſe muſt not bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted Heretiques, which beleeue not that all Emperours, Kings and Magiſtrates, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently all humane creatures are ſubiect to the power, and to the outward ſword of the Popes. But the Reformed Chriſtians eſteeme them to be Heretiques;<note place="margin">Who ought to be held for Heretiques.</note> Firſt of all, which bring into the Church of Chriſt, ſuch a doctrine as is repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Analogie and rule of Faith, briefly contained in the Apoſtles Creede. Secondly, ſuch as turne aſide from the true Catholique Church, that is to ſay, vniverſall: which retaines
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:8263:44"/>
the pure doctrine of God. And finally, ſuch as beeing often and ſeriouſly admoniſhed, doe not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding abſolutely perſevere in their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, for which they haue beene many times re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prehended and condemned.<note place="margin">The proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Church.</note> The Reformed now proteſt, that they haue not declined or gone aſtray one whit, from the Analogie and rule of Chriſtian Faith, and confeſſion of the faithfull, nor from the foure moſt ancient gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councels, that is to ſay, of <hi>Nice,</hi> of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and of <hi>Chalcedon;</hi> nor from the Creed of Saint <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> nor finally from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part of the Word of God. They further proteſt, that they were never lawfully cited in due and rightfull forme and manner, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by competent Iudges, nor convinced of any errors, but rather that they alwayes either rendred a reaſon, and made confeſſion of their Faith, or have appealed publiquely to a generall free Councell of all Chriſtendome: For tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">That the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Trent was not free.</note> that it was not free or open they can (as they ſay) cleerly proue by Hiſtories, in which it appeareth manifeſtly, that <hi>Cervinus Polus,</hi> and diuerſe other Cardinals were excluded from this Councell; as alſo <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques Nacluaiſt,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Clodiafoſſa; Dominicke Withelme</hi> of <hi>Venice; Paul Verger</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopolis,</hi> with certaine others; and that onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were ſuſpected ſomewhat to incline to the Reformed religion, and for certaine rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and ſpeeches which they deliuered or vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt the Popes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:8263:45"/>Concerning the ſending and calling of the Reformed Doctors, which firſt did repugne or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the Sea of Rome, the Reformed affirme, that they were called in part immediately, that is to ſay, they were called by God without any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward means, and that God diſpoſed their hearts, enflaming them with a true zeale for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of his glory, and of the kingdome of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt. In part alſo mediatly, that is to ſay, by outward meanes; that is, by the approving, enccouragement, and forwarding of Chriſtian Princes, Lords, and Magiſtrates, ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp by God for this purpoſe; as alſo diverſe Nations which with humble prayers praiſe the Lord for ſo great a grace and ſingular benefit of Reformation. And this is not onely lawfull for Chriſtian Princes and Magiſtrates to doe, but they are bound and tyed vnto it by the duty of their Calling at all times, when the outward and viſible ſtate of the Church requireth any refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of errors, which may haue crept into the Church by the malice or bad dealing and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Paſtors. That is manifeſtly percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved (ſay the Reformed) as well by the expreſſe commandement of God, in ſo many places of his Word, as by all the notable examples of <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kias, Ioſaphat, Ioſias,</hi> and diuerſe other religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Kings that feared God, who in their time cauſed the ſervice of God to be reformed, which was corrupted with Idolatry and ſuperſtition, as the holy Hiſtory at large doth teſtifie.</p>
               <p>Finally, whereas they of the Romane Church
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:8263:45"/>
accuſe the Reformed religion of nouelty.<note place="margin">The doctrine of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med is not new.</note> The Reformed Chriſtians therevpon complaine that thereby great wrong is done vnto Gods truth; becauſe the Reformed plainely ſhew that they neither acknowledge nor make profeſſion of any other doctrine then that by which <hi>Adam, Seth, Noe, Abraham,</hi> and all the other Patriarches and faithfull men haue beene ſaued, and the which our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, his Apoſtles, and the firſt ſix Counſels, and the moſt ancient Fathers, and Orthodoxe Doctors haue deliuered and ſet forth: So that finally the diuel, whileſt the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men did ſleep, hath filled the Lords field with ſo much darnell that the good corne can ſcarcely be diſcerned and perceaued: For albeit our Lord God hath alwayes firmly decreed to maintain &amp; continue his Church: yet his will is not that his Church ſhould be alwaies a like flouriſhing and proſperous, but like the moon he ſuffers it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time to encreaſe ſometimes to be in the waine or decreaſe,<note place="margin">Gen. 7. 1 King 19. Mat. 2.</note> euen ſo we ſee that in the time of <hi>Noe</hi> there were but eight perſons ſaued in the Arke from the waters of the flood. It is alſo ſayd that in the time of the Prophet <hi>Elias</hi> there were 7000. which embraced the true doctrine: Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe when the comming of Ieſus Chriſt was expected, the Church was ſo obſcure and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed that ſcarce one faithfull perſon ſeemed to be remaining.<note place="margin">How true do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine was by little falſified.</note> In like manner after the happie birth of our Sauiour the Chriſtian Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to decline by little and little for the ſpace of 1500 yeeres. For in the firſt 500. yeeres falſhood
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:8263:46"/>
began to oppoſe and reſiſt the truth. In the other 500. yeeres enſuing truth began to giue place to falſhood, and at the length in the laſt 500. yeeres truth was ſo ſubdued and oppoſed by falſhood, that ſhe could in a manner no where ſhew or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt her ſelfe. All this notwithſtanding, hence it followes not,<note place="margin">That the Church of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt was never wanting.</note> that the Church either hath been at ſometime aboliſhed or extinguiſhed and quite ſmoothered; or that the Reformed doe contend and ſtriue againſt the true Church. For the Church of Chriſt hath ever ſubſiſted, beene and continued, and ſhall endure ſo long time as the Lord Ieſus Chriſt ſhall raigne, vnder the ſure protection and ſafegard of whom it is ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and defended, howbeit notwithſtanding the outward forme is not alwayes alike viſible and apparent. So that the Reformed maintaine, that they impugne or go not againſt the true Church in any ſort, but together with the ſame they call vpon &amp; adore with perfect vnion one ſelfe-ſame God, belieue in one alone Ieſus Chriſt, who hath bin in all times called vpon &amp; worſhipped by all the faithfull children of God. But the Reformed Chriſtians proteſt on the other ſide, that they are ſeparated from that Synagogue or Aſſembly which hath not retained or preſerued true faith and religion, but aduanced humane traditions aboue divine Oracles, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> would lay vpon mens conſciences burdens inſupportable, which hath attempted imperiouſly to beare ſway ouer their faith, forbidden and hindered the pure preaching of the Word of God, and the due and rightfull
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:8263:46"/>
adminiſtration of the Sacraments, which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed yeerely to excommunicate them, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with all the Chriſtian Churches of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fricke, Egypt, Syria, Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Greece,</hi> which perſecuteth religious people, and ſuch as feare God, which will not admit or allow of any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; which corrupteth and blemiſheth things neceſſary in the Chriſtian Church; which hath made neceſſary things indifferent, and corrupted Lawes; which hath tyed the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique or vniverſall Church to one City. <hi>Orbem in Vrbe;</hi> briefly which is ſtained and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed with all kinde of ſinnes and iniquities. By reaſon whereof the Reformed againe proteſt, that they haue beene inforced to forſake this Aſſembly, to obey the commandement of God, and that they ought not to pollute nor charge their conſciences with the falſe Romiſh doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, leſt they be made partakers of the iuſt and fearfull puniſhments of God, which may befall the ſame.</p>
               <p>They of the Romane Church for a finall concluſion, demande hereupon,<note place="margin">Where the true Church hath beene ſo long hidden.</note> where the Church hath beene ſo long hidden. For if the Church of Rome (ſay they) hath not beene the true Catholique Church, muſt wee not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily condemne all thoſe which hitherto haue lived vnder the Popedome. The Reformed make anſwere, that there haue been found in all times Chriſtians, as well in the Eaſtern Chriſtian Churches, as alſo in the Weſterne, vnder the Popes iuriſdiction, which Chriſtians haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:8263:47"/>
thoſe Popiſh abuſes and corruptions: and which is more, hath ſometimes encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred them, both with liuely voyce and word of mouth,<note place="margin">In Regiſt. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>82.</hi> Ad Iohan. Ep. Conſtan. Epiſt. <hi>35.</hi> ad Maurit. Impera. Greg. Mag.</note> and by their bookes and writings; for not to ſpeake of the ancient Fathers, and of the Primitiue Church, which the Reformed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to haue beene wholly of one accord and conſent with them, in all the Articles of the true Faith and Chriſtian Religion: they can alſo plainely ſhew, that there haue beene ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in theſe laſt ages which haue conſented to the reformation of Religion. For albeit that <hi>Gregorie</hi> the Great maintained ſome errours, yet heerein hee held a good and ſound opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that hee is Antichriſt who ſuffereth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to bee called ſoveraigne or vniverſall Biſhop.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Everardus Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisburg.</note>
                  <hi>Everard</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salisberch,</hi> proved in an elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Oration which hee made at the Councell of <hi>Regensberch,</hi> that the Popes were Antichriſts, and that Pope <hi>Hildebrand</hi> layde the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this domination or ſoveraignty of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioachim Calaber. Franciſ. Petr.</hi> more then 800. yeares a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe.</note>
                  <hi>Ioachim Calaber</hi> at the ſame time did often call the Popes Antichriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Francis Petrarch</hi> in his writings, eſpecially in his twentith Epiſtle, hath very ſharply enveighed againſt the Popes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Arnulphus.</note>
                  <hi>Arnulph</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Orleance,</hi> openly at the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> called the Popes Antichriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Bernardus.</note>Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> in the yeere M. did challenge &amp; encounter the Popes as ſervants of Antichriſt.
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:8263:47"/>
At the ſame time <hi>Michael Centenas</hi> affirmed the Popes to be Antichriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ierome Sauanorola</hi> borne in <hi>Ferrara,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hieronymus Sauanorola.</note> preached throughout all <hi>Italy,</hi> that the Popes were Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts, alſo that their doctrine were prophane; for which he was burned at <hi>Florence</hi> by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas Reiden</hi> did abſolutely contemne and reiect the Popedome,<note place="margin">Thomas Reiden.</note> and was therefore alſo bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnder Pope <hi>Eugenius</hi> the fourth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laurentius Valla</hi> about an hundred yeeres paſt,<note place="margin">Laurentius Val.</note> called <hi>Rome Babylon,</hi> and the Pope Antichriſt: hee further ſaid, that the donation of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> was forged by the Popes themſelues, in ſuch ſort that hee oppoſed himſelfe earneſtly againſt the Popes; by reaſon whereof being exciled, he was very honourably receiued by the King of <hi>Naples.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Wickliffe</hi> did ſtoutly and worthily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne and reſiſt the Popedome in <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohann. Wickilf.</note> who was ſhortly after ſeconded by <hi>Iohn Hus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohannes Hus. Hieron. Prague.</note> and <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> of <hi>Prague,</hi> both which were impriſoned at the Councell of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> and there were alſo burned for the profeſſion of true religion. So that finally, an hundred yeeres after, followed <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> who more plainely expounded and layd open the true religion, and openly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred with the Popedome.</p>
               <p>Now the principall Potentates of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome haue endeavoured in diverſe ſorts and manners to hinder and reſtraine the great mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:8263:48"/>
of them that haue imbraced or followed this doctrine.<note place="margin">Diuers exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> doctrine.</note> For the Emperour <hi>Maximilian</hi> at <hi>Ausbureg</hi> in the yeere 1518. and <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, and <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> with divers other Kings and Princes; firſt of all, the yeere 1520. at <hi>Wormes;</hi> next, the yeere 1523. at <hi>Noremberch;</hi> afterwards, the yeere 1529. at <hi>Spires;</hi> after that, the yeere 1530. at <hi>Auſpurge;</hi> againe and finally, the yeere 1532. at <hi>Regensburge;</hi> and the yeere 1540. at <hi>Hagenau;</hi> All theſe Potentates aforeſayd (ſay the Reformed) at theſe ſundry times haue in part the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues heard the remonſtrance &amp; declaration of <hi>Luther,</hi> made with his owne mouth, &amp; in part cauſed his doctrine to bee examined by their owne Doctors.</p>
               <p>But afterwards when they perceived that by all their baniſhment, impriſonments, and by all the fire and gibbets, they could bring nothing to paſſe. They were at length conſtrained to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the counſell of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The counſell of <hi>Gamaliel.</hi> Act 5.</note> who adviſed the Iewes to permit the Apoſtles to preach; <hi>For if their worke were of men it would quickly come to naught; but if it were of Goa they could not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw it:</hi> Let every man then in like manner con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, or reſolue of the religion of the Reformed Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the meane while yee Kings, Princes, and all yee Inhabitants of the earth, who deſire to obtaine eternall ſalvation, bee wiſe and well adviſed, Serue the Lord with feare, and reioyce in him
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:8263:48"/>
with trembling. Kiſſe the Sonne leſt hee be angry, and yee periſh from the way. When his wrath is kindled but a little, bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
